<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><hi rend="underline">A Description of Mother Ludwell's Cave</hi>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="TNiese"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="R074$1L3" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">“ha Catabrae dulces et si mihi credis amaena.”</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">R074$1L3</l></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$1L3-line-1">R074$1L3   1  “Let others with Parnassus swell their theme,&#13;R074$1L3   2  Drink inspiration from the <unclear>AE</unclear>gean stream,R074$1L3   3  Let them draw Ph<unclear>oe</unclear>bus down to patch a line,R074$1L3   4  Invoke that hackney fry the tuneful nine.R074$1L3   5  I that of Ludwell sing, to Ludwell run,R074$1L3   6  Herself my muse, her spring my helicon.R074$1L3   7  The neighbouring Park its friendly aid allows,R074$1L3   8  Perfum'd with thyme, o'erspread with shadie boughs.R074$1L3   9  Its heavy canopies new thoughts instill,R074$1L3   10  And Crookesbury supplies the cloven hill;R074$1L3   11  Pomona does Minerva's stores dispense,R074$1L3   12  And Flora sheds her balmie influence.R074$1L3   13  All things conspire to press my modest muse:R074$1L3   14  The morning herbs adorn's with pearly dews,R074$1L3   15  The meadows interlaced with silver flouds,R074$1L3   16  The frizled thickets, and the taller woods,R074$1L3   17  The whispering Zephrs, my more silent tongueR074$1L3   18  Correct, and Philomela chirps a song.R074$1L3   19  Is there a bird of all the blooming yearR074$1L3   20  That has not sung his early mattins here?R074$1L3   21  That has not sipped the Fairy Matron's spring,R074$1L3   22  Or hover'd o'er her cave with wishful ring.R074$1L3   23  An awful fabric, built by nature's hand,R074$1L3   24  Does rise our wonder our respects command.R074$1L3   25  Three lucky trees to wilder art unknownR074$1L3   26  Seem on the front a growing triple crown.R074$1L3   27  At first the arched room is high and wide,R074$1L3   28  The naked wall with mossie hangings hid,R074$1L3   29  The ceiling sandy; as you forward pressR074$1L3   30  The roof is still declining into less.R074$1L3   31  Despair to reach the end, a little arch,R074$1L3   32  Narrow and low, forbids your utmost search;R074$1L3   33  So to her lover the chaste beauteous lassR074$1L3   34  Without a blush vouchsafes to show her face,R074$1L3   35  Her neck of ivory, her snowy breast──R074$1L3   36  These shown she modestly conceals the rest.R074$1L3   37  A shallow brook, that restless undergroundR074$1L3   38  Struggled with earth, here a moist passage found.R074$1L3   39  Down through a stoney vein the waters rowl,R074$1L3   40  O'er flowing the capacious iron bowl.R074$1L3   41  Oh! happy bowl that gladness can infuseR074$1L3   42  And yet was new stained with heavy juice.R074$1L3   43  Here thirsty souls carouse with innocence,R074$1L3   44  Nor owe their pleasure to their loss of sense.R074$1L3   45  Here a smooth floor had many a figure shewnR074$1L3   46  Had virgin footsteps made impression,R074$1L3   47  That soft and swift Camilla-like advanceR074$1L3   48  While even movements seem to fly a dance.R074$1L3   49  No quilted couch the sick man's daily bed,R074$1L3   50  No seats to lull asleep diseases madeR074$1L3   51  Are seen, but such as healthy persons pleaseR074$1L3   52  Of wood or stone, such as the wearied ease.R074$1L3   53  Oh! might I still enjoy this peaceful gloom!R074$1L3   54  The truest entrance to Elysium.R074$1L3   55  Who would to the Crimeen den repair,R074$1L3   56  A better Sybil, wiser power is here.R074$1L3   57  Methinks I see him from his Palace come,R074$1L3   58  And with his presence grace ye baleful ro<gap/>R074$1L3   59  Consider Ludwell what to him you owe,R074$1L3   60  Who does for you the noisey court forego.R074$1L3   61  Nay he a rich and gaudy silence leaves,R074$1L3   62  You share ye honour sweet Mooreparke receives.R074$1L3   63  You with yr wrinkles admiration moveR074$1L3   64  That with its beauty better merite love.R074$1L3   65  Here's careless nature is her ancient dress,R074$1L3   66  There she's most modish, and consults ye glass.R074$1L3   67  Here she's an old and yet a pleasant dame,R074$1L3   68  There she a fair not painted Virgin seem.R074$1L3   69  Here the rich mettal has through fire pass'dR074$1L3   70  There the refin'd by no alloy debas'd.R074$1L3   71  Thus nature is preserved in every part,R074$1L3   72  Sometimes adorn'd but not debauch'd by art,R074$1L3   73  Where scatter'd locks that dangle on the browR074$1L3   74  Into more decent haire circles grow.R074$1L3   75  After enquiry made though no man loveR074$1L3   76  The curling iron, all the comb approve.”R074$1L3   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
