<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-title-1">A description of Mother Ludwell's cave<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-title-1">1</ref><note n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-title-1" place="foot">`In the pleasure grounds of Moor Park, Surrey, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> W<hi rend="sup">m</hi> Temple's Seat' (note on the MS. perhaps written by the late Mrs. F. L. Longe).</note></title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="EBurnor"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-title-1 #spp-R074$3X1-title-1"/>
          <link target="# #spp-R074$3X1-footnote-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-1 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-2 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-3 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-4 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-5 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-6 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-7 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-8 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-9 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-10 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-11 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-12 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-13 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-14 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-15 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-16 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-17 #spp-R074$3X1-line-1"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="R074$3X1" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">hæ latebræ dulces, et si mihi credis, amœnæ<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-1">1</ref><note n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-1" place="foot"><hi rend="underline">hæ latebræ dulces, et si mihi credis, amœnæ</hi>. Horace, <hi rend="underline">Epist</hi>. I. xvi. 15: `Hae latebrae dulces, etiam, si credis, amoenae.' In the MS. this motto precedes <hi rend="underline">A Description</hi>, &amp;c</note></l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">R074$3X1</l></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-line-1" rend="indent(6)">R074$3X1   1  lett others with Parnassus swell their theam,&#13;R074$3X1   2  drinke inspiration from th' Aonian<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-1"><hi rend="underline">Aonian</hi>. Aonia was that part of B<unclear>oe</unclear>otia which contained Mount Helicon (treated in English poetry as a stream) and the fountain Aganippe.</note> stream:R074$3X1   3  lett them draw Ph<unclear>oe</unclear>bus down to patch a line,R074$3X1   4  invoke, that hackney fry,<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-2"><hi rend="underline">that hackney fry</hi>. Cp. Swift, <hi rend="underline">Ode to Sir William Temple</hi>, VII: `as in a theatre the ignorant fry.'</note> the tunefull nine:R074$3X1   5  I that of Ludwell sing, to Ludwell run,R074$3X1   6  her self my muse, her spring my Helicon.R074$3X1   7  the neighbouring park its friendly aid allows;R074$3X1   8  perfum'd with thyme, o'erspread with shadie boughs;R074$3X1   9  its leafie canopys new thoughts instill,R074$3X1   10  and Crooksberry<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-3">3</ref><note place="foot" n="3" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-3"><hi rend="underline">Crooksberry</hi>, a hill close to Moor Park.</note> supplies the cloven hill.<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-4">4</ref><note place="foot" n="4" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-4"><hi rend="underline">the cloven hill</hi>, Parnassus with its two peaks, the seat of the Muses.</note>R074$3X1   11  Pomona does Minerva<hi rend="sup">s</hi> stores dispence,<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-5">5</ref><note place="foot" n="5" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-5"><hi rend="underline">Pomona does Minerva<hi rend="sup">s<hi rend="underline"> stores dispense</hi></hi></hi>. If the line is sound, can it mean that Pomona is the agent of Temple, whose skill in fruit-tree lore was so well known? He chose the trees and gave them scientific culture, and Pomona then produced the apples.</note>R074$3X1   12  And Flora sheds her balmie influence;R074$3X1   13  all things conspire to press my modest Muse,R074$3X1   14  the morning herbs adorn'd with pearly dews,R074$3X1   15  the meadows interlaced with silver flouds,<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-6">6</ref><note place="foot" n="6" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-6"><hi rend="underline">the meadows interlaced with silver flouds</hi>, i.e. the Wey running through the water-meadows between Moor Park and Waverley (Sir A.H.).</note>R074$3X1   16  the frizled thickets,<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-7">7</ref><note place="foot" n="7" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-7"><hi rend="underline">the frizled thickets</hi>. Cp. Milton, <hi rend="underline">P.L</hi>. vii. 323: `And bush with frizzled haire implicit.' The reference is rather to the curled leaves than to their rustling sound.</note> and the taller woods.R074$3X1   17  the whisp'ring Zephyrs my more silent tongueR074$3X1   18  correct, and Philomela chirps a song.<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-8">8</ref><note place="foot" n="8" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-8"><hi rend="underline">Philomela chirps a song</hi>. Had the writer of these words ever heard a nightingale?</note>R074$3X1   19  is there a bird of all the blooming year,R074$3X1   20  that has not sung his early Mattins here?R074$3X1   21  that has not sip'd the Fairy Matron<hi rend="sup">s</hi><ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-9">9</ref><note place="foot" n="9" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-9"><hi rend="underline">the Fairy Matron<hi rend="sup">s</hi></hi>. `Fairy', as in `fairy godmother', with no suggestion of diminutive size.</note> spring,R074$3X1   22  or hover'd o'er her cave with wishfull wing?R074$3X1   23  an awfull Fabrick built by Nature<hi rend="sup">s</hi> handR074$3X1   24  does raise our wonder, our respect command.R074$3X1   25  three lucky trees to wilder art<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-10">10</ref><note place="foot" n="10" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-10"><hi rend="underline">wilder art</hi>. Nature is here less wild than Art: no gardener could get so artistic an effect.</note> unknownR074$3X1   26  seem on the front a growing triple crown.R074$3X1   27  at first the arched room is high and wide,R074$3X1   28  the naked walls with mossie hangings hid;R074$3X1   29  the cieling sandy: as you forward pressR074$3X1   30  the roof is still declining into less;R074$3X1   31  despair to reach the end──a little archR074$3X1   32  narrow and low forbids y<hi rend="sup">r</hi> utmost search.R074$3X1   33  so to her lover the chaste, beauteous lassR074$3X1   34  without a blush vouchsafes to shew her face,R074$3X1   35  her neck of Ivory, her snowy breast,R074$3X1   36  these shown, she modestly conceals the rest.R074$3X1   37  A shallow brook, that restless under groundR074$3X1   38  strugled with earth, here a moist passage found.R074$3X1   39  down thro' a stony vein the waters rowlR074$3X1   40  o'erflowing the capacious iron bowl:R074$3X1   41  oh! happy bowl, that gladness can infuse,R074$3X1   42  and yet was never stain'd with heady juice.R074$3X1   43  Here thirsty souls carouse with innocence,R074$3X1   44  nor owe their pleasure to their loss of sence.R074$3X1   45  Here a smooth floor had many a figure shown,R074$3X1   46  had Virgin footsteps made impression,R074$3X1   47  that soft and swift Camilla-like advance,<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-11">11</ref><note place="foot" n="11" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-11"><hi rend="underline">had Virgin footsteps made impression,_that soft and swift Camilla-like advance.</hi>_Virgil says of Camilla (<hi rend="underline">Aen</hi>. vii. 808, 9): `Illa vel intact<unclear>ae</unclear> segetis per summa volaret Gramina; nec teneras cursu l<unclear>ae</unclear>sisset aristas.' This Swift recalls in his poem <hi rend="underline">Sir William Temple's</hi> late <hi rend="underline">Illness and Recovery</hi> written in December 1693: `Time o'er the happy takes so swift a flight,  And treads so soft, so easy and so light,  That we the wretched, creeping far behind,  Can scarce th' impression of his footsteps find;  Smooth as that airy nymph so subtly born[e]  With inoffensive feet o'er standing corn.'_Were there two poets writing at Moor Park at the same time, whose minds separately recurred to Camilla? Or was Jonathan Swift the author of the `description of Mother Ludwells cave'? He refers to the cave in his lines to Mr. Congreve of the same year 1693: `Here by a mountain's side, a reverend cave  Gives murmuring passage to a lasting wave.' Pope's reference to the light-footed lady in <hi rend="underline">Essay on Criticism</hi>, ll. 372, 3 and Sir Walter Scott's in <hi rend="underline">The Lady of the Lake</hi>, I. xviii, are familiar to most people.</note>R074$3X1   48  while even movements seem to fly a dance.<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-12">12</ref><note place="foot" n="12" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-12"><hi rend="underline">while even movements seem to fly a dance</hi>. The line is difficult. I consider `a dance' as a cognate accusative. `Fly a dance'=`dance a dance'.</note>R074$3X1   49  no quilted couch, the sickman<hi rend="sup">s</hi> daily bed,R074$3X1   50  no seats to lull asleep diseases made,R074$3X1   51  are seen; but such as healthy persons pleaseR074$3X1   52  of wood or stone,<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-13">13</ref><note place="foot" n="13" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-13"><hi rend="underline">seats . . . of wood or stone</hi>. These seats, the iron bowl that received the waters from the inner cavern and overflowed with them, and the oaks mentioned in the other poem on the cave, are all well seen in the print of 1785.</note> such as the wearied ease.R074$3X1   53  O might I still enjoy this peacefull gloom!R074$3X1   54  the truest entrance to Elizium.R074$3X1   55  who would to the Cum<unclear>ae</unclear>an den<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-14">14</ref><note place="foot" n="14" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-14"><hi rend="underline">the Cum<unclear>ae</unclear>an den</hi>, the cave at Cum<unclear>ae</unclear> where Aeneas met the Sibyl, <hi rend="underline">Aen</hi>. vi. 42.</note> repaire?R074$3X1   56  a better Sybil, wiser power is here.R074$3X1   57  Methinks I see him from his palace come,R074$3X1   58  and with his presence grace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> balefull room:R074$3X1   59  Consider, Ludwell, what to him you owe,R074$3X1   60  who does for you the noisy court forego;<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-15">15</ref><note place="foot" n="15" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-15"><hi rend="underline">Consider, Ludwell, what to him you owe_who does for you the noisy court forego</hi>._This again resembles Swift's <hi rend="underline">Ode to Sir William Temple Written at Moor-Park in June 1689</hi>, stanza ix:_`Sing, beloved Muse! the pleasures of retreat . . ._Go, publish o'er the plain_How mighty a proselyte you gain!_How noble a reprisal on the great!'_Swift goes on to say that the Muse whom he invokes to leave the Thames for Moor Park at length `softly steals in many windings down, As loth to see the hated court and town'. Sir William Temple had left Sheen for Moor Park in 1681 after his son's marriage, had returned to Sheen during the troubles of the Revolution, and finally settled at Moor Park after his son's death in 1689. Swift lived with him at Moor Park from 1689 to 1691, from Feb. 1692 to May 1694, and from May 1696 till Temple's death on 26 Jan. 1698/9._The expression `debauch'd by praise' in stanza xii of this Ode is again an echo of l. 72 of the poem before us: `debauch'd by art.'</note>R074$3X1   61  nay he a rich and gaudy silence<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-16">16</ref><note place="foot" n="16" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-16"><hi rend="underline">a rich and gaudy silence</hi>. Temple has not only abandoned the Court, but his pleasant retirement at Sheen.</note> leaves,R074$3X1   62  you share y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honour, sweet Moorparke receives.R074$3X1   63  you with y<hi rend="sup">r</hi> wrinkles admiration move,R074$3X1   64  that with its beauty better merits love.R074$3X1   65  Here's careless Nature in her ancient dress,R074$3X1   66  there she·'s more modish,<ref target="#spp-R074$3X1-footnote-17">17</ref><note place="foot" n="17" xml:id="spp-R074$3X1-footnote-17"><hi rend="underline">modish</hi>. Swift speaks of `the new modish system' in his <hi rend="underline">Ode to the Athenian Society</hi>.</note> &amp; consults y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glass.R074$3X1   67  Here she·'s an old, but yet a pleasant dame;R074$3X1   68  there she'l a fair, not painted Virgin seem.R074$3X1   69  Here the rich Mettal hath through no fire pass'd,R074$3X1   70  there, tho refin'd, by no allay debas'd.R074$3X1   71  Thus nature is preserv'd in every part,R074$3X1   72  sometimes adorn'd, but nere debauch'd by art.R074$3X1   73  When scatter'd locks, that dangle on the brow,R074$3X1   74  into more decent hairy circles grow,R074$3X1   75  after enquiry made, tho no man loveR074$3X1   76  the curling iron, all the comb approve.R074$3X1   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
