<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>To the A<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">THENIAN </hi>S<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">OCIETY</hi>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="EWyble"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-016-07E2-footnote-1 #spp-016-07E2-line-18"/>
          <link target="#spp-016-07E2-footnote-2 #spp-016-07E2-line-87"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="016-07E2" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">G<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ENTLEMEN</hi>, Moor-park, Feb. 14. 1691.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">S</hi>Ince every body pretends to trouble you with their follies, I thought I might claim the privilege of an Englishman, and put in my share among the rest. Being last year in Ireland, (from whence I returned about half a year ago), I heard only a loose talk of your society, and believed the design to be only some new folly just suitable to the age, which God knows I little expected ever to produce any thing extraordinary. Since my being in England, having still continued in the country, and much out of company, I had but little advantage of knowing any more, till about two months ago passing through Oxford, a very learned gentleman there first shewed me two or three of your volumes, and gave me his account and opinion of you. A while after, I came to this place upon a visit to ────, where I have been ever since, and have seen all the four volumes, with their supplements; which answering my expectation, the perusal has produced what you find inclosed.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">As I have been somewhat inclined to this folly, so I have seldom wanted some body to flatter me in it. And for the ode inclosed, I have sent it to a person of very great learning and honour, and since to some others, the best of my acquaintance, (to which I thought very proper to enure it for a greater light); and they have all been pleased to tell me, that they are sure it will not be unwelcome; and that I should beg the honour of you to let it be printed before your next volume, (which, I think, is soon to be published); it being so usual before most books of any great value among poets: and before its seeing the world, I submit it wholly to the correction of your pens.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="4" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-4"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-4-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-4-line-group-1-line-1">I intreat therefore one of you would descend so far as to write two or three lines to me of your pleasure upon it. Which as I cannot but expect from gentlemen, who have so well shewn, upon so many occasions, that greatest character of scholars, in being favourable to the ignorant; so I am sure nothing at present can more highly oblige me, or make me happier. I am, <lb/> G<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ENTLEMEN</hi>, <lb/> Your ever most humble <lb/> and most admiring servant, <lb/> J<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ONATHAN </hi>S<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">WIFT</hi>.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="5" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-5"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-5-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-5-line-group-1-line-1">O<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">DE</hi> to the A<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">THENIAN </hi>S<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">OCIETY</hi>.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="6" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-6"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-6-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-headnote-6-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="underline">Moor-Park, Feb. 14. 1691</hi>.</l></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">A</hi>S when the deluge first began to fall,</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-2"> That mighty ebb never to flow again,</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-3"> (When this huge body's moisture was so great,It quite o'ercame the vital heat);</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-4"> That mountain which was highest, first of all</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-5"> Appear'd above the universal main,</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-6"> To bless the primitive sailor's weary sight;</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-7"> And 'twas perhaps Parnassus, if in height.It be as great as 'tis in fame,And nigh to heav'n as is its name:</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-8"> So after the inundation of a war,</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-9"> When learning's little household did imbark</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-10"> With her world's fruitful system in her sacred ark,At the first ebb of noise and fears,<hi rend="underline">Philosophy</hi>'s exalted head appears:</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-11"> And the dove-muse will now no longer stay,</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-12"> But plumes her silver wings, and flies away;And now a laurel wreath she brings from far,To crown the happy conqueror,To shew the flood begins to cease,</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-13" rend="align(center)"> And brings the dear reward of victory and peace.II.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="14" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-14" rend="flush left">The eager muse took wing upon the waves decline,&#13;When war her cloudy aspect just withdrew,When the bright sun of peace began to shine,</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-15"> And for a while in heav'nly contemplation satOn the high top of peaceful Ararat:</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-16"> And pluck'd a laurel branch, (for laurel was the first that grew,</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-17"> The first of plants after the thunder, storm, and rain),And thence with joyful, nimble wing,Flew dutifully back again,</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-18"> And made an humble chaplet <ref target="#spp-016-07E2-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-footnote-1">The ode I writ to the King in Ireland.</note> for the King.And the dove-muse is fled once more,</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-19"> (Glad of the victory, yet frighted at the war),And now discovers from afarA peaceful and a flourishing shore:No sooner did she landOn the delightful strand,Than strait she sees the country all around,Where fatal Neptune rul'd erewhile,</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-20"> Scatter'd with flow'ry vales, with fruitful gardens crown'd,And many a pleasant wood;As if the universal NileHad rather water'd it, than drown'd:</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-21"> It seems some floating piece of paradise,Preserv'd by wonder from the flood,</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-22"> Long wand'ring through the deep, as we are toldFam'd Delos did of old,And the transported muse imagin'd it</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-23"> To be a fitter birth-place for the god of wit,Or the much-talk'd oracular grove;When with amazing joy she hearsAn unknown music all around,Charming her greedy earsWith many a heav'nly song</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-24"> Of nature and of art, of deep philosophy and love,</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-25"> Whilst angels tune the voice, and God inspires the tongue.In vain she catches at the empty sound,</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-26" rend="align(center)"> In vain pursues the music with her longing eye,And courts the wanton echoes as they fly.III.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="27" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-27" rend="flush left">Pardon, ye great unknown, and far exalted men,&#13;</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-28"> The wild excursions of a youthful pen;Forgive a young, and (almost) virgin muse,Whom blind and eager curiosity(Yet curiosity, they say,</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-29"> Is in her sex a crime needs no excuse)Has forc'd to grope her uncouth way,</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-30"> After a mighty light that leads her wand'ring eye:</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-31"> No wonder then she quits the narrow path of sense,For a dear ramble through impertinence;Impertinence, the scurvy of mankind.</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-32"> And all we fools, who are the greater part of it,Though we be of two diff'rent factions still,Both the good natur'd and the ill;Yet wheresoe'er you look, you'll always find</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-33"> We join like flies, and wasps, in buzzing about wit.In me, who am of the first sect of these,All merit, that transcends the humble rulesOf my own dazzled scanty sense,Begets a kinder folly and impertinenceOf admiration and of praise.And our good brethren of the surly sectMust e'en all herd with us their kindred-fools:For though, possess'd of present vogue, they've made</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-34"> Railing a rule of wit, and obloquy a trade;</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-35"> Yet the same want of brains produces each effect.And you whom Pluto's helm does wisely shroudFrom us the blind and thoughtless croud,Like the fam'd hero in his mother's cloud,</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-36"> Who both our follies and impertinencies see,</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-37" rend="align(center)"> Do laugh perhaps at theirs, and pity mine and me.IV.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="38" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-38" rend="flush left">But censure's to be understood&#13;Th' authentic mark of the elect,</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-39"> The public stamp heav'n sets on all that's great and good,Our shallow search and judgment to direct.The war, methinks, has made</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-40"> Our wit and learning narrow as our trade;</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-41"> Instead of boldly sailing far to buy</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-42"> A stock of wisdom and philosophy,We fondly stay at home in fearOf ev'ry censuring privateer;</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-43"> Forcing a wretched trade by beating down the sale,And selling basely by retail.The wits, I mean the Atheists of the age,</l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-44"> Who fain would rule the pulpit, as they do the stage;Wondrous refiners of philosophy,Of morals and divinity,</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-45" rend="align(center)"> By the new modish system of reducing all to sense,Against all logic and concluding laws,Do own th' effects of providence,And yet deny the cause.V.</l></lg><lg n="5" type="stanza"><l n="46" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-46" rend="flush left">This hopeful sect, now it begins to see&#13;</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-47"> How little, very little do prevailTheir first and chiefest force,To censure, to cry down, and rail,</l><l n="48" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-48"> Not knowing what, or where, or who you be,Will quickly take another course:And by their never-failing waysOf solving all appearances they please,</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-49"> We soon shall see them to their ancient methods fall,</l><l n="50" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-50"> And straight deny you to be men, or any thing at all.I laugh at the grave answer they will make,</l><l n="51" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-51"> Which they have always ready, general, and cheap:'Tis but to say, that what we daily meet,And by a fond mistake</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-52"> Perhaps imagine to be wondrous wit,</l><l n="53" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-53"> And think, alas, to be by mortals writ,</l><l n="54" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-54"> Is but a croud of atoms justling in a heap,Which from eternal seeds begun,</l><l n="55" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-55" rend="align(center)"> Justling some thousand years till ripen'd by the sun;They're now, just now as naturally born,As from the womb of earth a field of corn.VI.</l></lg><lg n="6" type="stanza"><l n="56" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-56" rend="flush left">But as for poor contented me,&#13;</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-57"> Who must my weakness and my ignorance confess,</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-58"> That I believe in much, I ne'er can hope to see;Methinks I'm satisfy'd to guess,That this new, noble, and delightful scene</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-59"> Is wonderfully mov'd by some exalted men,Who have well studied in the world's disease,</l><l n="60" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-60"> (That epidemic error and depravity,Or in our judgment or our eye),That what surprises us can only please.</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-61"> We often search contentedly the whole world roundTo make some great discovery,And scorn it when 'tis found.</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-62"> Just so the mighty Nile has suffer'd in its fame,Because 'tis said (and perhaps only said)</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-63"> We've found a little inconsiderable head,That feeds the huge unequal stream.</l><l n="64" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-64"> Consider human folly, and you'll quickly own,That all the praises it can give,</l><l n="65" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-65"> By which some fondly boast they shall for ever live,Won't pay th'impertinence of being known:Else why should the fam'd Lydian king,</l><l n="66" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-66"> Whom all the charms of an usurped wife and state,</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-67"> With all that power unfelt, courts mankind to be great,Did with new unexperienc'd glories wait,</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-68" rend="align(center)"> Still wear, still dote on his invisible ring?VII.</l></lg><lg n="7" type="stanza"><l n="69" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-69" rend="flush left">Were I to form a regular thought of fame,&#13;Which is perhaps as hard t'imagine rightAs to paint <hi rend="underline">Echo</hi> to the sight;</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-70"> I would not draw th' idea from an empty name:Because, alas, when we all die,Careless and ignorant posterity,Although they praise the learning and the wit,And though the title seems to showThe name and man by whom the book was writ,Yet how shall they be brought to know,</l><l n="71" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-71"> Whether that very name was he, or you, or I?</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-72"> Less should I daub it o'er with transitory praise,And water-colours of these days:</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-73"> These days! where e'en th'extravagance of poetryIs at a loss for figures to expressMens folly, whimsies, and inconstancy,And by a faint description makes them less.</l><l n="74" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-74"> Then tell us, what is fame, where shall we search for it?</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-75"> Look where exalted Virtue and Religion sitInthron'd with heav'nly wit,Look where you seeThe greatest scorn of learned vanity,(And then how much a nothing is mankind!</l><l n="76" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-76"> Whose reason is weigh'd down by popular air,Who by that vainly talks of baffling death;And hopes to lengthen life by a transfusion of breath,Which yet who'er examines right, will findTo be an art as vain as bottling up of wind):</l><l n="77" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-77" rend="align(center)"> And when you find out these, believe true fame is there,Far above all reward, yet to which all is due;And this, ye great unknown, is only known in you.VIII.</l></lg><lg n="8" type="stanza"><l n="78" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-78" rend="flush left">The juggling sea-god, when by chance trepann'd&#13;</l><l n="79" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-79"> By some instructed querist sleeping on the sand,</l><l n="80" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-80"> Impatient of all answers, strait became</l><l n="81" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-81"> A stealing brook, and strove to creep awayInto his native sea,Vex'd at their follies, murmur'd in his stream;But disappointed of his fond desire,Would vanish in a pyramid of fire.This surly, slipp'ry god, when he design'dTo furnish his escapes,Ne'er borrow'd more variety of shapesThan you to please and satisfy mankind;</l><l n="82" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-82"> And seem (almost) transform'd to water, flame, and air,So well you answer all phenomena's there:</l><l n="83" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-83"> Though madmen and the wits, philosophers and fools,</l><l n="84" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-84"> With all that factious, or enthusiastic dotards dream,</l><l n="85" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-85"> And all the incoherent jargon of the schools;Though all the fumes of fear, hope, love, and shame,</l><l n="86" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-86"> Contrive to shock your minds with many a senseless doubt;</l><l n="87" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-87" rend="align(center)"> Doubts where the Delphic god would grope in ignorance and night,The god of learning and of lightWould want a <ref target="#spp-016-07E2-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-footnote-2"><unclear>Greek1</unclear></note> god himself to help him out.IX.</l></lg><lg n="9" type="stanza"><l n="88" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-88" rend="flush left">Philosophy, as it before us lies,&#13;</l><l n="89" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-89"> Seems to have borrow'd some ungrateful tasteOf doubts, impertinence, and niceties,From ev'ry age through which it pass'd,</l><l n="90" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-90"> But always with a stronger relish of the last.This beauteous queen, by heav'n design'dTo be the great original</l><l n="91" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-91"> For man to dress and polish his uncourtly mind,</l><l n="92" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-92"> In what mock-habits have they put her since the fall!More oft in fools and madmens hands than sages,She seems a medley of all ages,</l><l n="93" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-93"> With a huge fardingal to swell her fustian stuff,A new commode, a top-knot and a ruff,Her face patch'd o'er with modern pedantry,With a long sweeping train</l><l n="94" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-94" rend="align(center)"> Of comments and disputes, ridiculous and vain,All of old cut with a new die:How soon have you restor'd her charms,And rid her of her lumber and her books,Dress'd her again genteel and neat,And rather tight than great,How fond we are to court her to our arms!How much of heav'n is in her naked looks!X.</l></lg><lg n="10" type="stanza"><l n="95" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-95" rend="flush left">Thus the deluding muse oft blinds me to her ways,&#13;And ev'n my very thoughts transfersAnd changes all to beauty, and the praiseOf that proud tyrant sex of hers.The rebel-muse, alas, takes partBut with my own rebellious heart,</l><l n="96" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-96"> And you with fatal and immortal wit conspireTo fan th' unhappy fire.<hi rend="underline">Cruel unknown</hi>! what is it you intend?</l><l n="97" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-97"> Ah, could you, could you hope a poet for your friend!Rather forgive what my first transport said:</l><l n="98" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-98"> May all the blood, which shall by woman's scorn be shed,Lie upon you, and on your childrens head;</l><l n="99" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-99"> For you (ah, did I think I e'er should live to seeThe fatal time when that could be!)Have e'en increas'd their pride and cruelty.Woman seems now above all vanity grown,Still boasting of her great unknown</l><l n="100" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-100"> Platonic champions, gain'd without one female wile,Or the vast charges of a smile;Which 'tis a shame to see how much of lateYou've taught the cov'tous wretches to o'er-rate,</l><l n="101" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-101"> And which they've now the conscience to weighIn the same balance with our tears,And with such scanty wages payThe bondage and the slavery of years.</l><l n="102" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-102"> Let the vain sex dream on, their empire comes from us,And had they common generosity,They would not use us thus.Well────though you've rais'd her to this high degree,Ourselves are rais'd as well as she;And spite of all that they or you can do,'Tis pride and happiness enough to me</l><l n="103" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-103" rend="align(center)"> Still to be on the same exalted sex with you.XI.</l></lg><lg n="11" type="stanza"><l n="104" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-104" rend="flush left">Alas, how fleeting, and how vain,&#13;</l><l n="105" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-105"> Is even the nobler man, our learning and our wit!I sigh whene'er I think of it:As at the closing an unhappy sceneOf some great king and conqu'ror's death,When the sad melancholy muse</l><l n="106" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-106"> Stays but to catch his utmost breath.</l><l n="107" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-107"> I grieve, this noble work so happily begun,</l><l n="108" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-108"> So quickly and so wonderfully carry'd on,</l><l n="109" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-109"> Must fall at last to interest, folly, and abuse.There is a noon-tide in our lives,Which still the sooner it arrives,Although we boast our winter-sun looks bright,</l><l n="110" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-110"> And foolishly are glad to see it at its height,</l><l n="111" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-111"> Yet so much sooner comes the long and gloomy night.No conquest ever yet begun,</l><l n="112" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-112"> And by one mighty hero carried to its height,</l><l n="113" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-113"> E'er flourish'd under a successor or a son;</l><l n="114" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-114"> It lost some mighty pieces through all hands it past,</l><l n="115" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-115"> And vanish'd to an empty title in the last.For when the animating mind is fled,(Which nature never can retain,Nor e'er call back again),</l><l n="116" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-116" rend="align(center)"> The body, though gigantic, lies all cold and dead.XII.</l></lg><lg n="12" type="stanza"><l n="117" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-117" rend="flush left">And thus undoubtedly 'twill fare,&#13;With what unhappy men shall dareTo be successors to these great unknown,On Learning's high-establish'd throne.Censure, and Pedantry, and Pride,Numberless nations, stretching far and wide,</l><l n="118" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-118"> Shall (I foresee it) soon with Gothic swarms come forthFrom Ignorance's universal north,</l><l n="119" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-119"> And with blind rage break all this peaceful government:</l><l n="120" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-120"> Yet shall these traces of your wit remain,Like a just map, to tell the vast extentOf conquest in your short and happy reign;And to all future mankind shewHow strange a paradox is true,That men, who liv'd and dy'd without a name,</l><l n="121" xml:id="spp-016-07E2-line-121"> Are the chief heroes in the sacred list of fame.016-07E2   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
