<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>ODE.</title>
        <title>TO THE<lb/></title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="SRyder"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-016-91L--footnote-1 #spp-016-91L--line-17"/>
          <link target="#spp-016-91L--footnote-2 #spp-016-91L--line-70"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="016-91L-" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">TO THE Athenian Society.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="underline">Moor-park</hi>, Feb. 14. 1691.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">GENTLEMEN,</l></lg><lg n="2" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-3-line-group-2" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-3-line-group-2-line-1"><hi rend="italic-display-initial">S</hi><hi rend="underline">INCE </hi>every Body<hi rend="underline"> pretends to trouble you with their </hi>Follies<hi rend="underline">, I thought I might claim the Priviledge of an </hi>English-man<hi rend="underline">, and put in my share among the rest. Being last year in </hi>Ireland<hi rend="underline">, (from whence I returned about half a year ago) I heard only a </hi>loose talk of your Society<hi rend="underline">, and believed the design to be only some new </hi>Folly<hi rend="underline"> just suitable to the Age, which God knows, I little expected ever to produce any thing </hi>extra-<lb/>ordinary<hi rend="underline">. Since my being in </hi>England<hi rend="underline">, having still continued in the Countrey, and much out of Company; I had but little advantage of knowing any more, till about two Months ago </hi>passing through<hi rend="underline"> Oxford, </hi>a very learned Gentleman<hi rend="underline"> there, first shew'd me two or three of your </hi>Volumes<hi rend="underline">, and gave me his Account and Opinion of you; a while after, I came to this place, upon a Visit to ──────────where I have been ever since, and have seen all the </hi>four Volumes with their Supplements<hi rend="underline">, which answering my Expectation. The perusal has produced, what you find inclosed.</hi></l></lg></head><head type="note" n="4" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-4"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-4-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-4-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg><lg><hi rend="underline">As I have been somewhat inclined to this </hi>Folly<hi rend="underline">, so I have seldom wanted some-body to flatter me in it. And for the </hi>Ode<hi rend="underline"> inclosed, I have sent it to a Person of very great </hi>Learning and Honour<hi rend="underline">, and since to some others, the best of my Acquaintance, (</hi>to which I thought very proper to inure it for a greater light<hi rend="underline">) and they have all been pleased to tell me, that they are sure it will not be unwelcome, and that I should </hi>beg the Honour<hi rend="underline"> of You to let it be Printed before Your </hi>next Volume<hi rend="underline"> (which I think, is soon to be published,) it being so usual before most Books of any great value among Poets, and before it's seeing the World, I submit it wholly to the </hi>Correction of your Pens<hi rend="underline">.</hi></lg></head><head type="note" n="5" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-5"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-5-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-5-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="underline">I intreat therefore one of You would </hi>descend<hi rend="underline"> so far, as to write two or three lines to me of your Pleasure upon it. Which as I cannot but expect from Gentlemen, who have so well shewn upon so many occasions, that </hi>greatest Character<hi rend="underline"> of Scholars, in being favourable to the </hi>Ignorant<hi rend="underline">, So I am sure nothing at present, can more highly oblige me, or make me happier</hi>.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="6" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-6"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-6-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--headnote-6-line-group-1-line-1">I am, <lb/> (Gentlemen) <lb/> Your ever most Humble, <lb/> and most <lb/> admiring Servant. <lb/> <hi rend="underline">Jonathan Swift</hi>.</l></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-1" rend="align(center)">I.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="2" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-2" rend="flush left"><hi rend="display-initial">A</hi>S when the <hi rend="underline">Deluge</hi> first began to fall,That <hi rend="underline">mighty Ebb</hi> never to Flow again,(When this huge Bodies Moisture was so great</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-3"> It quite o'recame the vital Heat,)</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-4"> That Mountain which was highest first of all</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-5"> Appear'd, above the Universal Main,</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-6"> To bless the <hi rend="underline">Primitive Sailer</hi>'s weary sight,</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-7"> And 'twas perhaps <hi rend="underline">Parnassus</hi>, if in heightIt be as great as 'tis in Fame,And nigh to Heaven as is its Name.</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-8"> So after th' Inundation of a War</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-9"> When <hi rend="underline">Learnings little Houshold</hi> did embark</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-10"> With her World's fruitful System in her sacred Ark,At the first Ebb of Noise and Fears,<hi rend="underline">Philosophy</hi>'s exalted head appears;</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-11"> And the <hi rend="underline">Dove-muse</hi>, will now no longer stay</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-12" rend="align(center)"> But plumes her Silver Wings and flies away,And now a Laurel wreath she brings from far,To Crown the happy Conquerour,To shew the Flood begins to cease,And brings the dear Reward of <hi rend="underline">Victory and Peace</hi>.II.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="13" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-13" rend="flush left">The eager <hi rend="underline">Muse</hi> took wing upon the Waves decline,When War her cloudy aspect just withdrew,When the <hi rend="underline">Bright Sun</hi> of Peace began to shine,</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-14"> And for a while in heav'nly Contemplation sateOn the high Top of peaceful <hi rend="underline">Ararat</hi>;</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-15"> And pluckt a <hi rend="underline">Laurel</hi> branch (for Laurel was the first that grew,</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-16"> The first of Plants after the Thunder, Storm, and Rain)And thence with joyful, nimble WingFlew dutifully back again,</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-17"> And made an <hi rend="underline">Humble </hi><ref target="#spp-016-91L--footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-016-91L--footnote-1"><hi rend="underline">The Ode I writ to the King in</hi> Ireland.</note><hi rend="underline"> Chaplet for the King</hi>.And the <hi rend="underline">Dove-muse</hi> is fled once more,</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-18"> (Glad of the Victory, yet frighted at the War)And now discovers <hi rend="underline">from afar</hi>A Peaceful and a Flourishing Shore:No sooner does she landOn the delightful <hi rend="underline">Strand</hi>,When strait she sees the <hi rend="underline">Countrey all around</hi>,Where fatal <hi rend="underline">Neptune</hi> rul'd e'rewhile,</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-19"> Scatter'd with <hi rend="underline">flowry Vales</hi>, with fruitful Gardens crown'd,And many a pleasant Wood,As if the Universal <hi rend="underline">Nile</hi>Had rather water'd it, than drown'd:It seems some floating piece of <hi rend="underline">Paradice</hi>,Preserv'd by wonder from the Flood,Long <hi rend="underline">wandring thrô the Deep</hi>, as we are toldFam'd <hi rend="underline">Delos</hi> did of old,And the transported Muse imagin'd it</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-20"> To be a fitter <hi rend="underline">Birth-place for the God of Wit</hi>;Or the much-talkt Oracular GroveWhen with amazing Joy she hears,An <hi rend="underline">unknown Musick</hi> all around,Charming her greedy EarsWith many a heavenly Song</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-21"> Of Nature and of Art, of deep <hi rend="underline">Philosophy and Love,</hi><hi rend="underline">Whilst Angels tune the Voice, and God inspires the Tongue</hi>.In vain she catches at the empty Sound,</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-22" rend="align(center)"> In vain pursues the Musick with her longing Eye,And <hi rend="underline">Courts</hi> the wanton Echoes as they fly.III.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="23" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-23" rend="flush left">Pardon <hi rend="black-letter">Ye great Unknown</hi>, and far-exalted Men,</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-24"> The wild excursions of a youthful pen;Forgive a young and (almost) <hi rend="underline">Virgin-muse</hi>,Whom blind and eager Curiosity(Yet Curiosity they say,Is in her Sex a Crime needs no excuse)Has forc't to grope her uncouth way</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-25"> After a <hi rend="underline">mighty Light</hi> that leads her wandring Eye;</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-26"> No wonder then she quits the <hi rend="underline">narrow Path of Sense</hi>For a dear Ramble thro' Impertinence,Impertinence, the <hi rend="underline">Scurvy</hi> of Mankind,</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-27"> And all we Fools, who are the greater part of it,Tho' we be of two different Factions still,Both the Good-natur'd and the Ill,Yet wheresoe're you look you'll always find<hi rend="underline">We join like Flyes, and Wasps, in buzzing about Wit</hi>.In me, who am of the first Sect of these,All Merit that transcends the humble RulesOf my own dazled, scanty Sense</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-28"> Begets a kinder Folly and ImpertinenceOf Admiration and of Praise:And our good Brethren of the <hi rend="underline">Surly Sect</hi>Must e'en all herd with us their <hi rend="underline">Kindred Fools</hi>,For tho' possess'd of present Vogue they've made<hi rend="underline">Railing a Rule of Wit, and Obloquy a Trade</hi>,</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-29"> Yet the same want of Brains produces each effect;And you whom <hi rend="underline">Pluto</hi>'s Helm does wisely shroudFrom us the Blind and thoughtless Croud,Like the fam'd Hero in his Mother's Cloud,</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-30" rend="align(center)"> Who both our Follies and Impertinencies see,<hi rend="underline">Do laugh</hi> perhaps at theirs, and pity mine and me.IV.</l></lg><lg n="5" type="stanza"><l n="31" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-31" rend="flush left">But Censure's to be understood&#13;Th' <hi rend="underline">Authentick mark</hi> of the Elect,</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-32"> The publick Stamp Heav'n sets on all that's Great and Good,Our shallow Search and Judgment to direct.The War methinks has madeOur Wit and Learning, narrow as our Trade;Instead of boldly sailing far to buy<hi rend="underline">A Stock of Wisdom</hi> and Philosophy,We fondly stay at home in fear<hi rend="underline">Of ev'ry censuring Privateer</hi>,</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-33"> Forcing a wretched trade by beating down the sale,And selling <hi rend="underline">basely</hi> by Retail,<hi rend="underline">The Wits</hi>, I mean the Atheists of the Age,</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-34"> Who fain would rule the Pulpit, as they do the Stage,Wondrous <hi rend="underline">Refiners</hi> of Philosophy,Of Morals and Divinity,</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-35" rend="align(center)"> By the new <hi rend="underline">Modish System</hi> of reducing all to sense,Against all Logick and concluding Laws,Do own th' Effects of Providence,And yet deny the Cause.V.</l></lg><lg n="6" type="stanza"><l n="36" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-36" rend="flush left">This <hi rend="underline">hopeful Sect</hi>, now it begins to seeHow little, very little do prevailTheir <hi rend="underline">first and chiefest force</hi>To censure, to cry down, and rail,<hi rend="underline">Not knowing What, or Where, or Who, You be</hi>,Will quickly take another course,And by their never-failing waysOf Solving all Appearances they please,</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-37"> We soon shall see them to their ancient Methods fall,</l><l n="38" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-38"> And straight deny you to be <hi rend="underline">Men, or any thing at all</hi>;I laugh at the grave Answer they will make,</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-39" rend="align(center)"> Which they have always ready, general and Cheap;'Tis but to say, that what we daily meet,And by a fond mistakePerhaps imagine to be <hi rend="underline">wondrous Wit</hi>And think, alas, to be by mortals writ,Is but a <hi rend="underline">Crowd of Atoms</hi> justling in a heap,Which from Eternal Seeds begun,Justling some thousand years till ripen'd by the Sun,They're now, just now, as naturally born,As from the <hi rend="underline">Womb of Earth</hi> a field of Corn.VI.</l></lg><lg n="7" type="stanza"><l n="40" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-40" rend="flush left">But as for poor contented Me,&#13;</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-41"> Who must my Weakness and my Ignorance confess,</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-42"> That I believe in much, I ne're can hope to see;<hi rend="underline">Methinks I'm satisfied to guess</hi>That this New, Noble, and Delightful Scene</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-43"> Is wonderfully mov'd by some exalted Men,Who have well studied in the <hi rend="underline">Worlds Disease</hi>,</l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-44"> (That Epidemick Error and DepravityOr in our Judgement or our Eye)That what <hi rend="underline">surprises us</hi> can only please:</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-45"> We often search contentedly the whole World round,To make some <hi rend="underline">great Discovery</hi>,And scorn it when 'tis found.</l><l n="46" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-46"> Just so the Mighty <hi rend="underline">Nile</hi> has suffer'd in it's Fame,Because 'tis said, (and perhaps only said)</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-47"> We've found a little inconsiderable HeadThat feeds the huge unequal stream.</l><l n="48" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-48"> Consider <hi rend="underline">Humane Folly</hi>, and you'll quickly own,That all the Praises it can give,</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-49"> By which some fondly boast they shall for ever live,Won't pay th' <hi rend="underline">Impertinence</hi> of being known;Else why should the fam'd <hi rend="underline">Lydian</hi> King,</l><l n="50" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-50"> Whom all the <hi rend="underline">Charms</hi> of an Usurped Wife and State,</l><l n="51" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-51"> With all that Power unfelt, courts Mankind to be Great,Did with new, unexperienc't Glories wait,</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-52" rend="align(center)"> Still wear, still doat on his <hi rend="underline">Invisible Ring</hi>.VII.</l></lg><lg n="8" type="stanza"><l n="53" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-53" rend="flush left">Were I to form a regular <hi rend="underline">Thought of Fame</hi>,Which is perhaps as hard t'imagaine right<hi rend="underline">As to paint Eccho to the Sight</hi>:</l><l n="54" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-54"> I would not draw th' <hi rend="underline">Idea</hi> from an empty Name;Because, alas, when we all dyeCareless and Ignorant Posterity,Although they praise the Learning, and the Wit,And tho' the Title seems to showThe Name and Man, by whom the Book was writ,Yet how shall they be brought to know</l><l n="55" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-55"> Whether that very Name was <hi rend="underline">He, or You, or I</hi>?</l><l n="56" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-56"> Less should I dawb it o're with transitory Praise,And <hi rend="underline">water-colours</hi> of these Days,<hi rend="underline">These Days!</hi> where ev'n th' Extravagance of PoetryIs at a loss for Figures to expressMen's Folly, Whimsyes, and Inconstancy,And by a faint Description make them less.<hi rend="underline">Then tell us what is Fame</hi>? where shall we search for it?</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-57"> Look where exalted Vertue and Religion sitEnthron'd with Heav'nly Wit,Look where you seeThe greatest scorn of <hi rend="underline">Learned Vanity</hi>,(And then how much a nothing is Mankind!Whose Reason is weigh'd down by Popular air,</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-58"> Who by that, vainly talks of bafling Death,</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-59"> And hopes to lengthen Life by a <hi rend="underline">Transfusion of Breath</hi>,Which yet whoe're examines right will find</l><l n="60" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-60"> To be an Art as vain, as <hi rend="underline">Bottling up of Wind</hi>:)</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-61"> And when you find out these, believe true Fame is there.</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-62"> Far above all Reward, yet to which all is due,</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-63" rend="align(center)"> And this <hi rend="black-letter">Ye great Unknown</hi>, is only known in You.VIII.</l></lg><lg n="9" type="stanza"><l n="64" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-64" rend="flush left">The <hi rend="underline">Jugling Sea-god</hi> when by chance trepann'd</l><l n="65" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-65"> By some instructed <hi rend="underline">Querist</hi> sleeping on the Sand,Impatient of all <hi rend="underline">Answers</hi>, straight becameA <hi rend="underline">Stealing Brook</hi>, and strove to creep awayInto his Native Sea,Vext at their Follies murmur'd in his Stream;But disappointed of his fond DesireWould vanish in a <hi rend="underline">Pyramid of Fire</hi>.This Surly, <hi rend="underline">Slipp'ry God</hi>, when He design'dTo furnish his Escapes,Ne'er borrow'd more <hi rend="underline">variety of Shapes</hi>Than <hi rend="underline">You</hi> to please and satisfie Mankind,</l><l n="66" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-66" rend="indent(2)"> And seem (almost) transform'd to <hi rend="underline">Water, Flame, and Air,So well You answer all Ph<unclear>ae</unclear>nomenaes there</hi>;</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-67"> Tho' Madmen and the Wits, Philosophers and Fools,</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-68"> With all that Factious or Enthusiasticks Dotards dream,</l><l n="69" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-69"> And all the incoh<unclear>ae</unclear>rent Jargon of the Schools,Tho' all the Fumes of Fear, Hope, Love, and Shame,<hi rend="underline">Contrive to shock your Minds, with many a sensless doubt</hi>,</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-70" rend="align(center)"> Doubts, where the <hi rend="underline">Delphick God</hi> would grope in Ignorance and Night,The God of Learning and of Light<hi rend="underline">Would want a </hi><ref target="#spp-016-91L--footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-016-91L--footnote-2"><unclear>Greek shoulder note</unclear></note><hi rend="underline"> God Himself to help him out</hi>.IX.</l></lg><lg n="10" type="stanza"><l n="71" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-71" rend="flush left">Philosophy, as it before us lyes,&#13;Seems to have borrow'd some ungrateful tastOf <hi rend="underline">Doubts</hi>, Impertinence, and Niceties,From ev'ry Age through which it pass't,</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-72"> But always with a stronger relish of the Last.This beauteous Queen by Heaven design'dTo be the great Original</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-73"> For Man to <hi rend="underline">dress and polish</hi> his Uncourtly Mind,</l><l n="74" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-74"> In what <hi rend="underline">Mock-habits</hi> have they put her, since the Fall!More oft in Fools and Mad-mens hands than Sages<hi rend="underline">She seems a Medly of all Ages</hi>,</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-75"> With a huge Fardingal to swell her Fustian Stuff,A new Commode, a <hi rend="underline">Top-knot</hi>, and a Ruff,Her Face patch't o'er with <hi rend="underline">Modern Pedantry</hi>,With a long sweeping Train</l><l n="76" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-76" rend="align(center)"> Of Comments and Disputes, ridiculous and vain,<hi rend="underline">All of old Cut with a new Dye</hi>,How soon have You restor'd her Charms!And rid her of her <hi rend="underline">Lumber and Her Books</hi>,Drest her again Genteel and Neat,And rather Tite than Great,How fond we are to court Her to our Arms!<hi rend="underline">How much of Heav'n is in her naked looks</hi>.X.</l></lg><lg n="11" type="stanza"><l n="77" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-77" rend="flush left">Thus the <hi rend="underline">deluding Muse</hi> oft blinds me to her Ways,And ev'n my very Thoughts transfersAnd changes all to Beauty, and the PraiseOf that proud Tyrant Sex of Hers.The <hi rend="underline">Rebel Muse</hi>, alas, takes partBut with my own Rebellious Heart,</l><l n="78" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-78"> And You with <hi rend="underline">fatal and Immortal Wit</hi> conspireTo fann th' unhappy Fire:<hi rend="black-letter">Cruel Unknown</hi>! what is it You intend!</l><l n="79" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-79"> Ah, could You! could you hope <hi rend="underline">a Poet for your Friend</hi>!Rather forgive what my first Transport said,</l><l n="80" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-80"> May all the Blood, which shall by <hi rend="underline">Womans scorn</hi> be shedLye on you, and on your Childrens Head,</l><l n="81" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-81"> For You (ah, did I think I e'er should live to seeThe fatal Time when that cou'd be)Have ev'n encreas't their <hi rend="underline">Pride and Cruelty</hi>.Woman seems now above all Vanity grown,<hi rend="underline">Still boasting of Her Great Unknown</hi>;</l><l n="82" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-82"> Platonick Champions, gain'd without one Female Wile,Or the vast <hi rend="black-letter">Charges of a Smile</hi>;Which 'tis a shame to see how much of lateYou've taught the <hi rend="underline">Cov'tous</hi> Wretches to o're-rate,</l><l n="83" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-83"> And which they've now the Conscience to way<hi rend="underline">In the same Ballance with our Tears</hi>,And with such Scanty Wages payThe Bondage and the Slavery of Years.</l><l n="84" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-84" rend="align(center)"> Let the <hi rend="underline">vain sex</hi> dream on, their Empire comes from Us,And had they <hi rend="underline">common</hi> GenerosityThey would not use Us thus.Well──tho' you've rais'd Her to this high Degree,Our selves are rais'd as well as she,And 'spight of all that They or You can do,'Tis Pride and Happiness enough to Me<hi rend="underline">Still to be of the same exalted Sex with You</hi>.XI.</l></lg><lg n="12" type="stanza"><l n="85" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-85" rend="flush left">Alas, how fleeting, and how vain,&#13;</l><l n="86" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-86"> Is even the <hi rend="underline">nobler Man</hi>, our Learning, and our Wit,I sigh when e're I think of itAs at the closing an unhappy SceneOf some <hi rend="underline">great King</hi> and Conqu'rors Death,When the sad, melancholy MuseStays but to catch his <hi rend="underline">utmost breath</hi>,</l><l n="87" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-87"> I grieve, this Noble Work so happily begun,</l><l n="88" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-88"> So quickly, and so wonderfully carried on,</l><l n="89" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-89"> Must fall at last to Interest, Folly, and Abuse.There is a <hi rend="underline">Noon-tide</hi> in our LivesWhich still the sooner it arrives,Altho' we boast our <hi rend="underline">Winter-Sun looks bright</hi>,</l><l n="90" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-90"> And foolishly are glad to see it at it's height</l><l n="91" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-91"> Yet so much sooner comes the long and gloomy Night.No Conquest ever yet begun</l><l n="92" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-92"> And by one mighty Hero carried to it's height</l><l n="93" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-93"> E'er flourish't under a Successor or a Son;</l><l n="94" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-94"> It lost some mighty Pieces thro' all hands it past</l><l n="95" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-95"> And vanisht to an <hi rend="underline">empty Title in the Last</hi>.For when the animating Mind is fled,(Which Nature never can retain,Nor e'er call back again)</l><l n="96" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-96" rend="align(center)"> The Body, tho' Gigantick, lyes all <hi rend="underline">Cold and Dead</hi>.XII.</l></lg><lg n="13" type="stanza"><l n="97" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-97" rend="flush left">And thus undoubtedly 'twill fare,&#13;With what unhappy Men shall dare,<hi rend="underline">To be Successors to these Great Unknown</hi>,On Learning's high-establish't Throne.Censure, and Pedantry, and Pride,Numberless Nations, stretching far and wide,</l><l n="98" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-98"> Shall (I foresee it) soon with <hi rend="underline">Gothick</hi> Swarms come forthFrom Ignorance's Universal North,</l><l n="99" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-99"> And with blind Rage break all this peaceful Government;</l><l n="100" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-100"> Yet shall these <hi rend="underline">Traces of your Wit</hi> remainLike a <hi rend="underline">just Map</hi> to tell the vast ExtentOf Conquest in your short and Happy Reign;And to all future Mankind shewHow strange a <hi rend="underline">Paradox</hi> is true,<hi rend="underline">That Men, who liv'd and dy'd without a Name,</hi>.016-91L-   </l><l n="101" xml:id="spp-016-91L--line-101" rend="flush right"> Are the chief Heroes in the sacred List of Fame._Jonathan Swift</l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
