<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Description of an Irish Feast translated almost literally out of the Original Irish in the Year 1720.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="JIF"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-244-007D-footnote-1 #spp-244-007D-line-3"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="244-007D" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-1"><unclear>12 Irish lines (written in 11 lines) precede</unclear> O Rork's noble Fare will ne'er be forgot,by those who were there, or those who were not.</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-2"> His Revells to keep, we sup and we dine,On Seven Score Sheep, fat Bullocks and Swine.</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-3"> Usquebagh to our Feast, in Pails was brought up.an hundred at least, and a <ref target="#spp-244-007D-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-244-007D-footnote-1">wooden vessell</note> Madder our Cup.</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-4"> O there is the Sport, we rise with the Lightin disorderly Sort, from Snoring all Night.</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-5"> Oh how was I trickt. my Pipe it was brokemy Pocket was pick't. I lost my new Cloak</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-6"> I'm rifled, quoth Nell, of Mantle and Kerchiefwhy then fare them well, the De'ill take the Searcher</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-7"> Come Harper, strike up, but first by your FavourBoy, gi<unclear>blot</unclear> us a Cup, ay, this has Some Savour.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="8" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-8"><unclear>12 Irish lines follow, then...</unclear></l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-9"> O Rourk's jolly Boys. ne'er dreamt of the Matter'till rous'd by the Noise. and musicall Clatter</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-10"> They bounce from their Nest. no longer will tarrythey rise ready drest. without one Ave-Mary.</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-11"> They dance in a round. cuting Capers and rampinga Mercy the Ground. did not burst with their Stamping</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-12"> The Floor is all wet. with Leaps and with Jumpswhile the Water and Sweat. Splish Splash in their Pumps</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-13"> Bless you late and early. Loughlen O Enakinby my hand you dance rarely. Margery Greenagan</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-14"> Bring Straw for our bed. Shake it down to the Feetthen over us spread. the winnowing Sheet</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-15"> To shew I don't flinch. fill the Bowl up againthen give us a Pinch. of your Sneezing, a Yean.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="16" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-16"><unclear>12 Irish lines follow, then...</unclear></l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-17"> Good Lord, what a Sight. after all their good Chearfor People to fight. in the midst of their Beer:</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-18"> They rise from their Feast. and hot are their Brainsa Cubit at least. the Length of their Skeans</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-19"> What Stabs and what Cuts. what Clatt'ring of Stickswhat Strokes on Guts. what bastings and kicks!</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-20"> With Cudgels of Oak. well harden'd in Flamean hundred heads broke. an hundred Struck lame</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-21"> You Churl, I'll maintain. my Father built Luskthe Castle of Slane. and Carrick Drumrusk</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-22"> The Earl of Kidare. and Moynalta his brotheras great as they are. I was nurs'd by their Mother</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-23"> Ask that of old Madam. She'll tell you who's whoso far up as Adam. She knows it is true</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-24"> Come down with that Beam. if Cudgells are Scarcea Blow on the Weam. and Kick on the A──se.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="25" xml:id="spp-244-007D-line-25"><unclear>12 Irish lines follow</unclear>244-007D   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
