<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <hi rend="underline">Ode to the Athenian Society</hi>
        </title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="016-ROGP" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-1"> I</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="2" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-2">As when the deluge first began to fall,&#13;That mighty ebb never to flow again,</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-3"> (When this huge body's moisture was so great</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-4"> It quite o'ercame the vital heat,)</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-5"> That mountain which was highest first of all</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-6"> Appeared, above the universal main,</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-7"> To bless the primitive sailor's weary sight,</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-8"> And 'twas perhaps Parnassus, if in heightIt be as great as 'tis in fame,And nigh to heaven as is its name.</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-9"> So after the inundation of a war</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-10"> When Learning's little household did embark</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-11"> With her world's fruitful system in her sacred ark,At the first ebb of noise and fears,Philosophy's exalted head appears;</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-12"> And the dove-muse, will now no longer stay</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-13"> But plumes her silver wings and flies away,And now a laurel wreath she brings from far,To crown the happy conqueror,To show the flood begins to cease,And brings the dear reward of victory and peace.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="14" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-14">II</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="15" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-15">The eager muse took wing upon the waves' decline,&#13;When war her cloudy aspect just withdrew,When the bright sun of peace began to shine,</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-16"> And for a while in heavenly contemplation satOn the high top of peaceful Ararat;</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-17"> And plucked a laurel branch (for laurel was the first that grew,</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-18"> The first of plants after the thunder, storm and rain)And thence with joyful, nimble wingFlew dutifully back again,And made an humble chaplet for the King.And the dove-muse is fled once more,</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-19"> (Glad of the victory, yet frighted at the war)And now discovers from afarA peaceful and a flourishing shore:</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-20"> No sooner does she landOn the delightful strand,When straight she sees the country all around,Where fatal Neptune ruled e'rewhile,</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-21"> Scattered with flowery vales, with fruitful gardens crowned,And many a pleasant wood,As if the universal NileHad rather watered it, than drowned:It seems some floating piece of paradise,Preserved by wonder from the flood,Long wandering through the deep, as we are toldFamed Delos did of old,And the transported muse imagined it</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-22"> To be a fitter birthplace for the god of wit;Or the much-talked oracular groveWhen with amazing joy she hears,An unknown music all around,Charming her greedy earsWith many a heavenly song</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-23"> Of nature and art, of deep philosophy and love,</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-24"> Whilst angels tune the voice, and God inspires the tongue.In vain she catches at the empty sound,</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-25"> In vain pursues the music with her longing eye,And courts the wandering echoes as they fly.</l></lg><lg n="5" type="stanza"><l n="26" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-26">III</l></lg><lg n="6" type="stanza"><l n="27" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-27">Pardon <hi rend="underline">Ye great unknown</hi>, and far-exalted men,</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-28"> The wild excursions of a youthful pen;Forgive a young and (almost) virgin-muse,Whom blind and eager curiosity(Yet curiosity, they say,Is in her sex a crime needs no excuse)Has forced to grope her uncouth way</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-29"> After a mighty light that leads her wandering eye;</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-30"> No wonder then she quits the narrow path of senseFor a dear ramble through impertinence,Impertinence, the scurvy of mankind,</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-31"> And all we fools, who are the greater part of it,Though we be of two different factions still,Both the good-natured and the ill,Yet wheresoe'er you look you'll always find</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-32"> We join like flies, and wasps, in buzzing about wit.In me, who am of the first sect of these,All merit that transcends the humble rulesOf my own dazzled, scanty senseBegets a kinder folly and impertinenceOf admiration and of praise:And our good brethren of the surly sectMust e'en all herd with us their kindred fools,For though possessed of present vogue, they've made</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-33"> Railing a rule of wit, and obloquy a trade,</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-34"> Yet the same want of brains produces each effect;And you whom Pluto's helm does wisely shroudFrom us the blind and thoughtless crowd,Like the famed hero in his mother's cloud,</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-35"> Who both our follies and impertinences see,</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-36"> Do laugh perhaps at theirs, and pity mine and me.</l></lg><lg n="7" type="stanza"><l n="37" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-37">IV</l></lg><lg n="8" type="stanza"><l n="38" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-38">But censure's to be understood&#13;The authentic mark of the elect,</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-39"> The public stamp heaven sets on all that's great and good,Our shallow search and judgement to direct.The war methinks has madeOur wit and learning, narrow as our trade;Instead of boldly sailing far to buyA stock of wisdom and philosophy,We fondly stay at home in fearOf every censuring privateer,</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-40"> Forcing a wretched trade by beating down the sale,And selling basely by retail,The wits, I mean the atheists of the age,</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-41"> Who fain would rule the pulpit, as they do the stage,Wondrous reformers of philosophy,Of morals and divinity,</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-42"> By the new modish system of reducing all to sense,Against all logic and concluding laws,Do own the effects of Providence,And yet deny the cause.</l></lg><lg n="9" type="stanza"><l n="43" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-43">V</l></lg><lg n="10" type="stanza"><l n="44" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-44">This hopeful sect, now it begins to see&#13;</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-45"> How little, very little do prevailTheir first and chiefest forceTo censure, to cry down, and rail,</l><l n="46" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-46"> Not knowing what, or where, or who, you be,Will quickly take another courseAnd by their never-failing waysOf solving all appearances they please,</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-47"> We soon shall see them to their ancient methods fall,</l><l n="48" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-48"> And straight deny you to be men, or anything at all;I laugh at the grave answer they will make,</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-49"> Which they have always ready, general and cheap;'Tis but to say, that what we daily meet,And by a fond mistakePerhaps imagine to be wondrous witAnd think, alas, to be by mortals writ,Is but a crowd of atoms jostling in a heap,Which from eternal seeds begun,Jostling some thousand years till ripened by the sun,They're now, just now, as naturally born,As from the womb of earth a field of corn.</l></lg><lg n="11" type="stanza"><l n="50" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-50">VI</l></lg><lg n="12" type="stanza"><l n="51" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-51">But as for poor contented me,&#13;</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-52"> Who must my weakness and my ignorance confess,</l><l n="53" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-53"> That I believe in much, I ne'er can hope to see;Methinks I'm satisfied to guessThat this new, noble, and delightful scene</l><l n="54" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-54"> Is wonderfully moved by some exalted men,Who have well studied in the world's disease,</l><l n="55" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-55"> (That epidemic error and depravityOr in our judgement or our eye)That what <hi rend="underline">surprises</hi> us can only please:</l><l n="56" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-56"> We often search contentedly the whole world round,To make some great discovery,And scorn it when 'tis found.</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-57"> Just so the mighty Nile has suffered in its fame,Because 'tis said, (and perhaps only said)</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-58"> We've found a little inconsiderable headThat feeds the huge unequal stream.</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-59"> Consider human folly, and you'll quickly own,That all the praises it can give,</l><l n="60" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-60"> By which some fondly boast they shall for ever live,Won't pay the impertinence of being known;Else why should the famed Lydian king,</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-61"> Whom all the charms of an usurped wife and state,</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-62"> With all that power unfelt, courts mankind to be great,Did with new, unexperienced glories wait,</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-63"> Still wear, still doat on his invisible ring.</l></lg><lg n="13" type="stanza"><l n="64" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-64">VII</l></lg><lg n="14" type="stanza"><l n="65" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-65">Were I to form a regular thought of fame,&#13;Which is perhaps as hard t'imagine rightAs to paint Echo to the sight:</l><l n="66" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-66"> I would not draw the idea from an empty name;Because, alas when we all dieCareless and ignorant posterity,Although they praise the learning and the wit,And though the title seems to showThe name and man, by whom the book was writ,Yet how shall they be brought to know</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-67"> Whether that very name was he, or you, or I?</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-68"> Less should I daub it o'er with transitory praise,And water-colours of these days,</l><l n="69" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-69"> These days! where even the extravagance of poetryIs at a loss for figures to expressMen's folly, whimsies, and inconstancy,And by a faint description makes them less.</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-70"> Then tell us what is fame? where shall we search for it?</l><l n="71" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-71"> Look where exalted virtue and religion sitEnthroned with heavenly wit,Look where you seeThe greatest scorn of learned vanity,(And then how much a nothing is mankind!Whose reason is weighed down by popular air,</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-72"> Who by that, vainly talks of baffling death,</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-73"> And hopes to lengthen life by a transfusion of breath,Which yet whoe'er examines right will find</l><l n="74" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-74"> To be an art as vain, as bottling up of wind:)</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-75"> And when you find out these, believe true fame is there.</l><l n="76" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-76"> Far above all reward, yet to which all is due,</l><l n="77" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-77"> And this <hi rend="underline">ye great unknown</hi>, is only known in you.</l></lg><lg n="15" type="stanza"><l n="78" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-78">VIII</l></lg><lg n="16" type="stanza"><l n="79" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-79">The juggling sea-god when by chance trepanned&#13;</l><l n="80" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-80"> By some instructed querist sleeping on the sand,Impatient of all answers, straight becameA stealing brook, and strove to creep awayInto his native sea,Vexed at their follies, murmured in his stream;But disappointed of his fond desireWould vanish in a pyramid of fire.This surly, slippery god, when he designedTo furnish his escapes,Ne'er borrowed more variety of shapesThan you to please and satisfy mankind,</l><l n="81" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-81"> And seem (almost) transformed to water, flame, and air,So well you answer all phenomenas there;</l><l n="82" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-82"> Though madmen and the wits, philosophers and fools,</l><l n="83" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-83"> With all that factious or enthusiastic dotards dream,</l><l n="84" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-84"> And all the incoherent jargon of the schools,Though all the fumes of fear, hope, love, and shame,</l><l n="85" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-85"> Contrive to shock your minds, with many a senseless doubt,</l><l n="86" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-86"> Doubts, where the Delphic god would grope in ignorance and night,The god of learning and of lightWould want a god himself to help him out.</l></lg><lg n="17" type="stanza"><l n="87" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-87">IX</l></lg><lg n="18" type="stanza"><l n="88" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-88">Philosophy, as it before us lies,&#13;Seems to have borrowed some ungrateful tasteOf doubts, impertinence, and niceties,From every age through which it passed,</l><l n="89" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-89"> But always with a stronger relish of the last.This beauteous queen by heaven designedTo be the great original</l><l n="90" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-90"> For man to dress and polish his uncourtly mind,</l><l n="91" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-91"> In what mock-habits have they put her, since the Fall!More oft in fools' and madmen's hands than sages'She seems a medley of all ages,</l><l n="92" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-92"> With a huge fardingale to swell her fustian stuff,A new commode, a topknot, and a ruff,Her face patched o'er with modern pedantry,With a long sweeping train</l><l n="93" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-93"> Of comments and disputes, ridiculous and vain,All of old cut with a new dye,How soon have you restored her charms!And rid her of her lumber and her books,Dressed her again genteel and neat,And rather tight than great,How fond we are to court her to our arms!How much of heaven is in her naked looks.</l></lg><lg n="19" type="stanza"><l n="94" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-94">X</l></lg><lg n="20" type="stanza"><l n="95" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-95">Thus the deluding muse oft blinds me to her ways,&#13;And even my very thoughts transfersAnd changes all to beauty, and the praiseOf that proud tyrant sex of hers.The rebel muse, alas, takes partBut with my own rebellious heart,</l><l n="96" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-96"> And you with fatal and immortal wit conspireTo fan the unhappy fire:<hi rend="underline">Cruel unknown</hi>! what is it you intend!</l><l n="97" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-97"> Ah, could you! could you hope a poet for your friend!Rather forgive what my first transport said,</l><l n="98" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-98"> May all the blood, which shall by woman's scorn be shedLie on you, and on your children's head,</l><l n="99" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-99"> For you (ah, did I think I e'er should live to seeThe fatal time when that could be)Have even increased their pride and cruelty.Woman seems now above all vanity grown,Still boasting of her great unknown;</l><l n="100" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-100"> Platonic champions, gained without one female wile,Or the vast <hi rend="underline">charges of a smile</hi>;Which 'tis a shame to see how much of lateYou've taught the covetous wretches to o'errate,</l><l n="101" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-101"> And which they've now the conscience to weighIn the same balance with our tears,And with such scanty wages payThe bondage and the slavery of years.</l><l n="102" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-102"> Let the vain sex dream on, their empire comes from us,And had they common generosityThey would not use us thus.Well──though you've raised her to this high degree,Ourselves are raised as well as she,And spite of all that they or you can do,'Tis pride and happiness enough to me</l><l n="103" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-103"> Still to be of the same exalted sex with you.</l></lg><lg n="21" type="stanza"><l n="104" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-104">XI</l></lg><lg n="22" type="stanza"><l n="105" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-105">Alas, how fleeting, and how vain,&#13;</l><l n="106" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-106"> Is even the nobler man, our learning and our wit,I sigh whene'er I think of itAs at the closing an unhappy sceneOf some great king and conqueror's death,When the sad, melancholy museStays but to catch his utmost breath,</l><l n="107" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-107"> I grieve, this noble work so happily begun,</l><l n="108" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-108"> So quickly, and so wonderfully carried on,</l><l n="109" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-109"> Must fall at last to interest, folly, and abuse.There is a noontide in our livesWhich still the sooner it arrives,Although we boast our winter sun looks bright,</l><l n="110" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-110"> And foolishly are glad to see it at its height</l><l n="111" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-111"> Yet so much sooner comes the long and gloomy night.No conquest ever yet begun</l><l n="112" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-112"> And by one mighty hero carried to its height</l><l n="113" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-113"> E'er flourished under a successor or a son;</l><l n="114" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-114"> It lost some mighty pieces through all hands it passed</l><l n="115" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-115"> And vanished to an empty title in the last.For when the animating mind is fled,(Which nature never can retain,Nor e'er call back again)</l><l n="116" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-116"> The body, though gigantic, lies all cold and dead.</l></lg><lg n="23" type="stanza"><l n="117" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-117">XII</l></lg><lg n="24" type="stanza"><l n="118" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-118">And thus undoubtedly 'twill fare,&#13;With what unhappy men shall dare,To be successors to these great unknown,On Learning's high-established throne.Censure, and Pedantry, and Pride,Numberless nations, stretching far and wide,</l><l n="119" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-119"> Shall (I foresee it) soon with Gothic swarms come forthFrom Ignorance's universal north,</l><l n="120" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-120"> And with blind rage break all this peaceful government;</l><l n="121" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-121"> Yet shall these traces of your wit remainLike a just map to tell the vast extentOf conquest in your short and happy reign;And to all future mankind showHow strange a paradox is true,That men, who lived and died without a name,</l><l n="122" xml:id="spp-016-ROGP-line-122"> Are the chief heroes in the sacred list of fame.016-ROGP   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
