<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:id="spp-016-14W2-title-1">ODE TO THE SOCIETY.<ref target="#spp-016-14W2-footnote-title-1">1</ref><note n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-footnote-title-1" place="foot">“I have been told, that Dryden having perused these verses, said, 'Cousin Swift, you will never be a poet;' and that this denunciation was the motive of Swift's perpetual malevolence to Dryden.”──J<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">OHNSON</hi></note></title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="AGendler"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-016-14W2-footnote-title-1 #spp-016-14W2-title-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-016-14W2-footnote-1 #spp-016-14W2-line-20"/>
          <link target="#spp-016-14W2-footnote-2 #spp-016-14W2-line-31"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="016-14W2" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="underline">Moor Park, Feb</hi>. 14, 1691.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">T<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">HE</hi> noted John Dunton, an author and bookseller, who often afterwards encountered the edge of Swift's ridicule, about the year 1690-1, set forth a literary plan, or project, as he called it, for an association of wits, to be entitled, The Athenian Society. According to his own account, the body, thus formed, was only second to the Royal Society, which led him justly to express his admiration, why the “great Sprat did not oblige the age with a <hi rend="underline">second best</hi> history of the second best institution for the promotion of learning and removing epidemic ignorance.” If the knowledge of this second best institution was at all inferior to that of their great prototype, their readiness of communication made some amends; for they proposed not only to answer curious queries in divinity, physic, law, philosophy, history, poetry, mathematics, trade, and all other questions proposed by either sex, or in any language, but also to give a complete review of all new publications; and, in case they were favoured with the communication of any curious experiment, to insert it in their Mercury, with a demonstration which the sender could not adhibit to it. This promising annunciation instantly produced a volley of queries, some grave, some gay, some in mockery, and some in sad earnest; all which the society answered in their Weekly Mercuries, with more learning, and with as much dulness as might have been expected from their assurance. The Athenian Mercuries extended at length to twenty volumes, from which were selected three octavo volumes, 1706, and a supplement in 1710, entitled the Athenian Oracle, and professing to contain an entire collection of what was valuable in the publications of the society.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">That Swift should have looked up with admiration to this “Oracle, this wooden God,” can only be pardoned by those who have known in what extraordinary and disproportionate respect an author who has attained, however unworthily, the attention of the public, is regarded by a young man whose instinctive talents for literature lead him to estimate the labours of such a person, less by their intrinsic merit, than by their having attained the reward of public notice, to which his own secret feelings induce him to aspire. It cannot, however, be disguised, that Swift, though he might regret having offered incense at so unworthy a shrine, had no cause to lament the value of the tribute. In point of poetical merit, the Athenian Society did not merit a more valuable eulogy than the following ode; and assuredly it does not exceed even their deserts.</l></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-1" rend="align(center)">I.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="2" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-2" rend="flush left">As when the deluge first began to fall,&#13;That mighty ebb never to flow again,</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-3"> When this huge body's moisture was so great,It quite o'ercame the vital heat;</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-4"> That mountain which was highest, first of all</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-5"> Appear'd above the universal main,</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-6"> To bless the primitive sailor's weary sight;</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-7"> And 'twas perhaps Parnassus, if in heightIt be as great as 'tis in fame,And nigh to Heaven as is its name;</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-8"> So, after the inundation of a war,</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-9"> When learning's little household did embark,</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-10"> With her world's fruitful system, in her sacred ark,At the first ebb of noise and fears,</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-11"> Philosophy's exalted head appears;</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-12"> And the Dove-Muse will now no longer stay,</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-13"> But plumes her silver wings, and flies away;And now a laurel wreath she brings from far,To crown the happy conqueror,To shew the flood begins to cease,</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-14"> And brings the dear reward of victory and peace.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="15" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-15" rend="align(center)">II.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="16" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-16" rend="flush left">The eager Muse took wing upon the waves' decline,&#13;When war her cloudy aspect just withdrew,When the bright sun of peace began to shine,</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-17"> And for a while in heavenly contemplation sat,On the high top of peaceful Ararat;</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-18"> And pluck'd a laurel branch, (for laurel was the first that grew,</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-19"> The first of plants after the thunder, storm, and rain,)And thence, with joyful, nimble wing,Flew dutifully back again,</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-20"> And made an humble chaplet for the king.<ref target="#spp-016-14W2-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-footnote-1">The Ode I writ to the king in Ireland.──S<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">WIFT</hi>.──See this in p. 21.</note>And the Dove-Muse is fled once more,</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-21"> (Glad of the victory, yet frighten'd at the war,)And now discovers from afarA peaceful and a flourishing shore:No sooner did she landOn the delightful strand,Than straight she sees the country all around,Where fatal Neptune ruled erewhile,</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-22"> Scatter'd with flow'ry vales, with fruitful gardens crown'dAnd many a pleasant wood;As if the universal NileHad rather water'd it than drown'd:</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-23"> It seems some floating piece of Paradise,Preserved by wonder from the flood,</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-24"> Long wandering through the deep, as we are toldFamed Delos did of old;And the transported Muse imagined it</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-25"> To be a fitter birth-place for the God of wit,Or the much-talk'd-of oracular grove;When, with amazing joy, she hears</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-26"> An unknown music all around,Charming her greedy earsWith many a heavenly song</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-27"> Of nature and of art, of deep philosophy and love;</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-28"> While angels tune the voice, and God inspires the tongue.In vain she catches at the empty sound,</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-29"> In vain pursues the music with her longing eye,And courts the wanton echoes as they fly.</l></lg><lg n="5" type="stanza"><l n="30" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-30" rend="align(center)">III.</l></lg><lg n="6" type="stanza"><l n="31" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-31" rend="flush left">Pardon, ye great unknown, and far-exalted men,<ref target="#spp-016-14W2-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-footnote-2">I cannot help inserting one question put to these “great unknown, and far-exalted men,” with their sapient response. What Swift would have thought of their dulness at a future period of his life, it is vain to inquire._“<hi rend="underline">Query</hi>. Since in your advertisement you make it known, that a chirurgeon is taken into your society, I have thought fit to propound the following question, withal assuring you the matter of fact is true. A sailor on board the fleet, by an unlucky accident broke his leg, being in drink, and refusing the assistance of the surgeon of the ship, called for a piece of new tarpaulin that lay on the deck, which he roled some turns about his leg, tying up all close with a few hoopsticks, and was able immediately to walk round the ship, never keeping his bed one day. I would know whether the cure is not to be attributed to the emplastic nature of the tarred cloth bound on strait with the hoopsticks, &amp;c. or rather, whether it may not be solved according to the Cartesian philosophy?_“<hi rend="underline">Answer</hi>. Des Cartes has less to do with this question than Copernicus, who, in a drunken fit, by the course of his brain, found out the great secret of the world's turning round; and so might our drunken sailor be inspired with this novel way of curing himself. But to the question, If the lesser focile was only broken, he might not be decumbent one day; the greater (his head being pretty light) being able to support his body; but if both the bones were broken, he could not stand, unless the splinters that were tied round his leg came below his heel, and rested upon his ham, which would take away that weight the leg would otherwise bear. Besides, the tarpaulin is a good categmatic, which, with a sober and a regular diet, might succeed, though it is no rule to walk by.”──<hi rend="underline">Athenian Oracle</hi>, vol. II. p. 349._It is hardly necessary to point out to the reader, unless qualified by nature to join the Athenian Society, that the fracture must have befallen a <hi rend="underline">wooden</hi> leg.</note></l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-32"> The wild excursions of a youthful pen;Forgive a young and (almost) virgin Muse,Whom blind and eager curiosity(Yet curiosity, they say,</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-33"> Is in her sex a crime needs no excuse)Has forced to grope her uncouth way,</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-34"> After a mighty light that leads her wandering eye:</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-35"> No wonder then she quits the narrow path of senseFor a dear ramble through impertinence;</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-36"> Impertinence! the scurvy of mankind.</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-37"> And all we fools, who are the greater part of it,Though we be of two different factions still,Both the good-natured and the ill,Yet wheresoe'er you look, you'll always find</l><l n="38" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-38"> We join, like flies and wasps, in buzzing about wit.In me, who am of the first sect of these,All merit, that transcends the humble rulesOf my own dazzled scanty sense,</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-39"> Begets a kinder folly and impertinenceOf admiration and of praise.</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-40"> And our good brethren of the surly sect,Must e'en all herd us with their kindred fools:For though, possess'd of present vogue, they've made</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-41"> Railing a rule of wit, and obloquy a trade;</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-42"> Yet the same want of brains produces each effect.And you, whom Pluto's helm does wisely shroudFrom us, the blind and thoughtless crowd,Like the famed hero in his mother's cloud,</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-43"> Who both our follies and impertinences see,</l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-44"> Do laugh perhaps at theirs, and pity mine and me.</l></lg><lg n="7" type="stanza"><l n="45" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-45" rend="align(center)">IV.</l></lg><lg n="8" type="stanza"><l n="46" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-46" rend="flush left">But censure's to be understood&#13;Th' authentic mark of the elect,</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-47"> Th' public stamp Heaven sets on all that's great and good,Our shallow search and judgment to direct.The war, methinks, has made</l><l n="48" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-48"> Our wit and learning narrow as our trade;</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-49"> Instead of boldly sailing far, to buy</l><l n="50" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-50"> A stock of wisdom and philosophy,We fondly stay at home, in fearOf every censuring privateer;</l><l n="51" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-51"> Forcing a wretched trade by beating down the sale,And selling basely by retail.The wits, I mean the atheists of the age,</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-52"> Who fain would rule the pulpit, as they do the stage,Wondrous refiners of philosophy,Of morals and divinity,</l><l n="53" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-53"> By the new modish system of reducing all to sense,Against all logic, and concluding laws,Do own th' effects of Providence,And yet deny the cause.</l></lg><lg n="9" type="stanza"><l n="54" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-54" rend="align(center)">V.</l></lg><lg n="10" type="stanza"><l n="55" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-55" rend="flush left">This hopeful sect, now it begins to see&#13;</l><l n="56" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-56"> How little, very little, do prevailTheir first and chiefest forceTo censure, to cry down, and rail,</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-57"> Not knowing what, or where, or who you be,Will quickly take another course:And, by their never-failing waysOf solving all appearances they please,</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-58"> We soon shall see them to their ancient methods fall,</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-59"> And straight deny you to be men, or anything at all.I laugh at the grave answer they will make,</l><l n="60" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-60"> Which they have always ready, general, and cheap:'Tis but to say, that what we daily meet,And by a fond mistake</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-61"> Perhaps imagine to be wondrous wit,</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-62"> And think, alas! to be by mortals writ,</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-63"> Is but a crowd of atoms justling in a heap:Which, from eternal seeds begun,</l><l n="64" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-64"> Justling some thousand years, till ripen'd by the sun:They're now, just now, as naturally born,As from the womb of earth a field of corn.</l></lg><lg n="11" type="stanza"><l n="65" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-65" rend="align(center)">VI.</l></lg><lg n="12" type="stanza"><l n="66" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-66" rend="flush left">But as for poor contented me,&#13;</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-67"> Who must my weakness and my ignorance confess,</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-68"> That I believe in much I ne'er can hope to see;Methinks I'm satisfied to guess,That this new, noble, and delightful scene,</l><l n="69" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-69"> Is wonderfully moved by some exalted men,Who have well studied in the world's disease,</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-70"> (That epidemic error and depravity,Or in our judgment or our eye,)</l><l n="71" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-71"> That what surprises us can only please.</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-72"> We often search contentedly the whole world round,To make some great discovery,And scorn it when 'tis found.</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-73"> Just so the mighty Nile has suffer'd in its fame,Because 'tis said (and perhaps only said)</l><l n="74" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-74"> We've found a little inconsiderable head,That feeds the huge unequal stream.</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-75"> Consider human folly, and you'll quickly own,That all the praises it can give,</l><l n="76" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-76"> By which some fondly boast they shall for ever live,Won't pay th' impertinence of being known:Else why should the famed Lydian king,</l><l n="77" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-77"> (Whom all the charms of an usurped wife and state,</l><l n="78" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-78"> With all that power unfelt, courts mankind to be great,Did with new unexperienced glories wait,)</l><l n="79" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-79"> Still wear, still doat on his invisible ring?</l></lg><lg n="13" type="stanza"><l n="80" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-80" rend="align(center)">VII.</l></lg><lg n="14" type="stanza"><l n="81" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-81" rend="flush left">Were I to form a regular thought of Fame,&#13;Which is, perhaps, as hard t'·imagine right,As to paint Echo to the sight,</l><l n="82" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-82"> I would not draw the idea from an empty name;Because, alas! when we all die,Careless and ignorant posterity,Although they praise the learning and the wit,And though the title seems to shewThe name and man by whom the book was writ,Yet how shall they be brought to know,</l><l n="83" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-83"> Whether that very name was he, or you, or I?</l><l n="84" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-84"> Less should I daub it o'er with transitory praise,And water-colours of these days:</l><l n="85" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-85"> These days! where e'en th' extravagance of poetryIs at a loss for figures to expressMen's folly, whimseys, and inconstancy,And by a faint description makes them less.</l><l n="86" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-86"> Then tell us what is Fame, where shall we search for it?</l><l n="87" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-87"> Look where exalted Virtue and Religion sit,Enthroned with heavenly Wit!Look where you seeThe greatest scorn of learned vanity!(And then how much a nothing is mankind!</l><l n="88" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-88"> Whose reason is weigh'd down by popular air,Who, by that, vainly talks of baffling death;And hopes to lengthen life by a transfusion of breath,Which yet whoe'er examines right will findTo be an art as vain as bottling up of wind!)</l><l n="89" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-89"> And when you find out these, believe true Fame is there,Far above all reward, yet to which all is due:And this, ye great unknown! is only known in you.</l></lg><lg n="15" type="stanza"><l n="90" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-90" rend="align(center)">VIII.</l></lg><lg n="16" type="stanza"><l n="91" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-91" rend="flush left">The juggling sea-god, when by chance trepann'd&#13;</l><l n="92" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-92"> By some instructed querist sleeping on the sand,Impatient of all answers, straight becameA stealing brook, and strove to creep awayInto his native sea,Vex'd at their follies, murmur'd in his stream;But disappointed of his fond desire,Would vanish in a pyramid of fire.This surly, slippery God, when he design'dTo furnish his escapes,Ne'er borrow'd more variety of shapes</l><l n="93" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-93"> Than you, to please and satisfy mankind,</l><l n="94" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-94"> And seem (almost) transform'd to water, flame, and air,So well you answer all phenomena there:</l><l n="95" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-95"> Though madmen and the wits, philosophers and fools,</l><l n="96" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-96"> With all that factious or enthusiastic dotards dream,</l><l n="97" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-97"> And all the incoherent jargon of the schools;Though all the fumes of fear, hope, love, and shame,</l><l n="98" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-98"> Contrive to shock your minds with many a senseless doubt;</l><l n="99" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-99"> Doubts where the Delphic God would grope in ignorance and night,The God of learning and of lightWould want a God himself to help him out.</l></lg><lg n="17" type="stanza"><l n="100" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-100" rend="align(center)">IX.</l></lg><lg n="18" type="stanza"><l n="101" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-101" rend="flush left">Philosophy, as it before us lies,&#13;</l><l n="102" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-102"> Seems to have borrow'd some ungrateful tasteOf doubts, impertinence, and niceties,From every age through which it pass'd,</l><l n="103" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-103"> But always with a stronger relish of the last.This beauteous queen, by Heaven design'dTo be the great original</l><l n="104" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-104"> For man to dress and polish his uncourtly mind,</l><l n="105" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-105"> In what mock habits have they put her since the fall!More oft in fools and madmen's hands than sages',She seems a medley of all ages,</l><l n="106" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-106"> With a huge farthingale to swell her fustian stuff,A new commode, a topknot, and a ruff,Her face patch'd o'er with modern pedantry,With a long sweeping train</l><l n="107" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-107"> Of comments and disputes, ridiculous and vain,All of old cut with a new dye:How soon have you restored her charms,And rid her of her lumber and her books,Drest her again genteel and neat,And rather tight than great!</l><l n="108" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-108"> How fond we are to court her to our arms!How much of heaven is in her naked looks!</l></lg><lg n="19" type="stanza"><l n="109" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-109" rend="align(center)">X.</l></lg><lg n="20" type="stanza"><l n="110" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-110" rend="flush left">Thus the deluding Muse oft blinds me to her ways,&#13;And ev'n my very thoughts transfersAnd changes all to beauty and the praiseOf that proud tyrant sex of hers.The rebel Muse, alas! takes part,But with my own rebellious heart,</l><l n="111" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-111"> And you with fatal and immortal wit conspireTo fan th' unhappy fire.Cruel unknown! what is it you intend?</l><l n="112" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-112"> Ah! could you, could you hope a poet for your friend!Rather forgive what my first transport said:</l><l n="113" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-113"> May all the blood, which shall by woman's scorn be shed,Lie upon you and on your children's head!</l><l n="114" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-114"> For you (ah! did I think I e'er should live to seeThe fatal time when that could be!)Have even increased their pride and cruelty.Woman seems now above all vanity grown,Still boasting of her great unknown</l><l n="115" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-115"> Platonic champions, gain'd without one female wile,Or the vast charges of a smile;Which 'tis a shame to see how much of lateYou've taught the covetous wretches to o'errate,</l><l n="116" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-116"> And which they've now the consciences to weighIn the same balance with our tears,And with such scanty wages payThe bondage and the slavery of years.</l><l n="117" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-117"> Let the vain sex dream on; the empire comes from us;And had they common generosity,They would not use us thus.Well──though you've raised her to this high degree,Ourselves are raised as well as she;And, spite of all that they or you can do,</l><l n="118" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-118"> 'Tis pride and happiness enough to me,</l><l n="119" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-119"> Still to be of the same exalted sex with you.</l></lg><lg n="21" type="stanza"><l n="120" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-120" rend="align(center)">XI.</l></lg><lg n="22" type="stanza"><l n="121" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-121" rend="flush left">Alas, how fleeting and how vain&#13;</l><l n="122" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-122"> Is even the nobler man, our learning and our wit!I sigh whene'er I think of it:As at the closing of an unhappy sceneOf some great king and conqueror's death,When the sad melancholy Muse</l><l n="123" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-123"> Stays but to catch his utmost breath.</l><l n="124" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-124"> I grieve, this nobler work, most happily begun,</l><l n="125" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-125"> So quickly and so wonderfully carried on,</l><l n="126" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-126"> May fall at last to interest, folly, and abuse.There is a noontide in our lives,Which still the sooner it arrives,</l><l n="127" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-127"> Although we boast our winter sun looks bright,</l><l n="128" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-128"> And foolishly are glad to see it at its height,</l><l n="129" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-129"> Yet so much sooner comes the long and gloomy night.No conquest ever yet begun,</l><l n="130" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-130"> And by one mighty hero carried to its height,</l><l n="131" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-131"> E'er flourish'd under a successor or a son;</l><l n="132" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-132"> It lost some mighty pieces through all hands it pass'd,</l><l n="133" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-133"> And vanish'd to an empty title in the last.For, when the animating mind is fled,(Which nature never can retain,Nor e'er call back again,)</l><l n="134" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-134"> The body, though gigantic, lies all cold and dead.</l></lg><lg n="23" type="stanza"><l n="135" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-135" rend="align(center)">XII.</l></lg><lg n="24" type="stanza"><l n="136" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-136" rend="flush left">And thus undoubtedly 'twill fare&#13;With what unhappy men shall dareTo be successors to these great unknown,On learning's high-establish'd throne.Censure, and Pedantry, and Pride,</l><l n="137" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-137"> Numberless nations, stretching far and wide,</l><l n="138" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-138"> Shall (I foresee it) soon with Gothic swarms come forthFrom Ignorance's universal North,</l><l n="139" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-139"> And with blind rage break all this peaceful government:</l><l n="140" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-140"> Yet shall the traces of your wit remain,Like a just map, to tell the vast extentOf conquest in your short and happy reign:And to all future mankind shewHow strange a paradox is true,That men who lived and died without a name</l><l n="141" xml:id="spp-016-14W2-line-141"> Are the chief heroes in the sacred lists of fame.016-14W2   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
