<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>To their Excellencies &amp;────</title>
        <title>The Humble Petition of Frances Harris,<lb/></title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="JW"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-069-002D-footnote-1 #spp-069-002D-line-27"/>
          <link target="#spp-069-002D-footnote-2 #spp-069-002D-line-28"/>
          <link target="#spp-069-002D-footnote-3 #spp-069-002D-line-49"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="069-002D" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-1">Humbly sheweth,</l></lg><lg n="2" type="triplet"><l n="2" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-2">That I went to warm my self in Lady Bettey's Chamber because I was cold,&#13;</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-3"> And I had in a Purse, 7<hi rend="sup">lḷ</hi> and 4<hi rend="sup">s</hi> (besides Farthings) in Money and Gold;</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-4"> So because I had been buying things for My Lady last Night,</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-5"> I was resolv'd to tell my Money, to see if it was right:</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-6"> Now You must know, because my Trunk has a very bad Lock,</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-7"> Therefore all the Money I have, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> God knows is a Very small stock,</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-8"> I keep in a Pocket ty'd about my Middle, next my Smock.</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-9"> So when I put up my Purse, as God wou'd have it, my smock was unript,</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-10"> And instead of putting it into My Pocket, down it slipt:</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-11"> Then the Bell rung, and I went down stairs to put my Lady to Bed,</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-12"> When, God knows, I thought my Money was as safe as my Maiden-head.<gap/></l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-13"> But when I search'd, and miss'd My Purse, Lord! I thought I shou'd have sunk outright.</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-14"> Lord! Madam, says Mary, how d'yee do? Indeed says I, never worse;</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-15"> But pray, Mary, can Y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> tell what I have done with My Purse!</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-16"> Lord help me, said Mary, I never stirr'd out of this Place!</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-17"> Nay, said I, I had it in Lady Betty's Chamber, that's a plain case.</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-18"> So Mary got me to Bed, and Cover'd me up Warm,</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-19"> However She stole away by Garters, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I might do My self no harm:</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-20"> So I tumbl'd and toss'd all night, as Y<hi rend="sup">ụ</hi> may very well think,</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-21"> But hardly ever set my Eyes together, or slept a Wink.</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-22"> So I was dream'd, Methought that we Went and search'd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> folks round,</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-23"> And in a Corner of M<hi rend="sup">rṣ</hi> Duke's Box, ty'd in a Rag, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> money was found.</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-24"> So next morning We told Whittle, and he fell a swearing,</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-25"> Then M<hi rend="sup">rṣ</hi> Wadgar came, and she, Y<hi rend="sup">ụ</hi> know is thick of hearing;</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-26"> Dame, said I, as loud as I cou'd Bawl, do You know what a loss I have had?</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-27"> Nay, said she, my Lord <ref target="#spp-069-002D-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-069-002D-footnote-1">Gallway.</note> Collway's Folks are all Very sad,</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-28"> For my L<hi rend="sup">ḍ</hi><ref target="#spp-069-002D-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-069-002D-footnote-2">Drogheda</note> Dromedary comes a Tuesd: without fail;</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-29"> Pugh! said I, but that's not the Business that I ail.</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-30"> Says Cary, says he, I have been a serv<hi rend="sup">t</hi>: this 5 and Twenty Years come spring</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-31"> And in all the Places I Liv'd, I never heard of such a thing.</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-32"> Yes, says the Steward, when I was at My Lady Shrewsbury's</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-33"> Such a thing as this happen'd just about the Time of Goosberries.</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-34"> So I went to the Party suspected, and found Her full of Grief,</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-35"> Now You know, of all things in the World, I hate a Thief:</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-36"> However, I was resolv'd to bring the discourse slily about,</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-37"> M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Dukes, said I, here's an ugly Accident has happen'd out;</l><l n="38" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-38"> 'Tis not that I Value the Money three Skips of a Louse.</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-39"> But the thing I stand upon, is the Credit of the house;</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-40"> Tis true 7<hi rend="sup">lḷ</hi> and 4<hi rend="sup">ṣ</hi> and 6<hi rend="sup">ḍ</hi> makes a great Hole in my Wages,</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-41"> Besides as they say, Service is no Inheritance in these Ages.</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-42"> Now, M<hi rend="sup">rṣ</hi> Dukes, You know and ev'ry body understands</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-43"> That tho' tis hard to Judge-- Money cannot go without hands.</l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-44"> The Devil take me, says she, Blessing her self, if ever I saw't!</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-45"> So she Roar'd like a Bedlam, as tho' I had call'd her to naught;</l><l n="46" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-46"> So You know, what cou'd I say to her any more,</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-47"> I e'en Left her, and came away as Wise as I was before.</l><l n="48" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-48"> Well: but then they wou'd have had me Gone to the Cunning-Man;</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-49"> No, said I, 'tis the same Thing, The <ref target="#spp-069-002D-footnote-3">3</ref><note place="foot" n="3" xml:id="spp-069-002D-footnote-3">Doc<hi rend="sup">tṛ</hi> Jonath<hi rend="sup">n</hi>: Swift then Chaplain to L<hi rend="sup">ḍ</hi> Berkly (one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> L<hi rend="sup">d'ṣ</hi> Justices) and suppos'd Author of this whimsical and humorous Petition.</note> Chaplain will be here anon.</l><l n="50" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-50"> So the Chaplain came in; Now the Serv<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>: say he is my Sweet-heart,</l><l n="51" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-51"> Because he's always in My Chamber, and I allways take his part;</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-52"> So, as the Devil wou'd have it, before I was Aware, out I Blunder'd,</l><l n="53" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-53"> Parson, said I, can You cast a Nativity? when a Body's Plunder'd?</l><l n="54" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-54"> Now You must know, he hates to be call'd Parson like the Devil,</l><l n="55" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-55"> Truly, said he M<hi rend="sup">rṣ</hi> Nab, it might become You to be more civil:</l><l n="56" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-56"> If Your Money begone, as a Learned Divine says, d'Ye see,</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-57"> You are no Text for my handling, take that from Me:</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-58"> I was never taken for a Conjurer before, I'd have You to know.</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-59"> Lord, said I, don't be Angry, I'm sure I never thought You so;</l><l n="60" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-60"> You know I honour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cloth, I design to be a Parson's Wife,</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-61"> I never took One in Y<hi rend="sup">ṛ</hi> Coat for a Conjurer in all My Life.</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-62"> With that he Twisted his Girdle like a Rope, as who shou'd say,</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-63"> Now You may go hang Your self for Me, and so went away.</l><l n="64" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-64"> Well I thought I shou'd have swoon'd; Lord, said I, what shall I do?</l><l n="65" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-65"> I have lost My Money, and shall loose My True Love too.</l><l n="66" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-66"> Then My Lord call'd me; Harris, said My Lord, don't Cry,</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-67"> I'll give something towards thy Loss; and says my Lady, so will I.</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-68"> Oh, but said I, what if after all, My Chaplain won't come to?</l><l n="69" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-69"> For that he said, (an't please Your Excellencies) I must petition You.</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-70"> The Premises tenderly Consider'd, I desire Y<hi rend="sup">ṛ</hi> Excellencys Protection,</l><l n="71" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-71"> And that I may have a share in next Sunday's Collection:</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-72"> And over and above, that I may have Your Excellency's Letter</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-73"> With an Order for the Chaplain aforesaid; or instead of him a better:</l><l n="74" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-74"> And then Your poor Petitioner, both Night and Day</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-069-002D-line-75"> Or the Chaplain, for 'tis his Trade, as in Duty bound, shall Pray:069-002D   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
