<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Saint <hi rend="underline">PATRICK</hi>'s<lb/></title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="EBurnor"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-102-40L2-footnote-1 #spp-102-40L2-line-23"/>
          <link target="#spp-102-40L2-footnote-2 #spp-102-40L2-line-28"/>
          <link target="#spp-102-40L2-footnote-3 #spp-102-40L2-line-28"/>
          <link target="#spp-102-40L2-footnote-4 #spp-102-40L2-line-36"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="102-40L2" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">T</hi>HE Nature and End of Divine Prophecy having been learnedly discuss'd by that excellent Theological and Political Prelate of our Church, Dr. <hi rend="underline">Thomas Sherlock, secundum usum</hi> S<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ARUM</hi>, we shall not attempt any thing in its Defence. The true Motive of publishing this Paper is, to do Justice to the Patron Saint of the good Kingdom of <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>, and totally obviate the Prejudices conceived by the Ignorant against the most learned Science of Astrology.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1">For a farther Vindication of this famous Art, we shall refer to the Prophecy here produced; the Original of which is the genuine Production of the Saint above mentioned:</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1">The Translation here given of it is above two hundred Years old; for it seems to be written near the End of <hi rend="underline">Henry</hi> the VIIth's Reign, and was found in a very recluse subterraneous Cavern, and brought to light by our truly orthodox Dean in the Year 1709. We have given it faithfully Word for Word, in the old Orthography, and subjoined thereto the explanatory Notes he made.</l></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-1" rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="underline">Seven and Ten</hi><«FN1· rend="align(center) flush left">By another Copy lately discover'd, we find it thus:_<hi rend="underline">When </hi>one, seven, three<hi rend="underline">, are join'd to </hi>nyne<hi rend="underline">,_Of </hi>Spain<hi rend="underline"> her Woe this is the Sygne..»</hi><hi rend="underline"> addyd to nyne,</hi>.<unclear>endnotes</unclear>E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">XPLANATORY </hi>N<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">OTES</hi>._<hi rend="underline">Seven and Ten</hi>. This Line describes the Year when these Events shall happen._</«FN1·></l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-2"> Of Fraunce hir Woe thys is the Sygne;</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-3"> Tamys rivere twys y-frozen,</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-4"> Walke sans methyngo Shoes ne Hozen:</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-5"> Then comyth foorthe, Ich understonde,</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-6"> From Toune of Stoffe to fattyn Londe,</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-7"> An herdie Chiftan, Woe the Morne</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-8"> To Fraunce, that evere he was borne.</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-9"> Than shall the Fyshe beweyle his Bosse;</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-10"> Nor shall grin Berrys make up the Losse.</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-11"> Yonge Symnele shall again miscarrye;</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-12"> And Norways Pryd again shall marrey.</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-13"> And from the Tree where Blosums fele,</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-14"> Ripe fruit shall come and all is wele.</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-15"> Reaums shall daunce honde in honde.</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-16"> And it shall be merye in olde Inglonde,</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-17"> Then old Inglonde shall be no more,</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-18"> And no Man shall be sorie therefore.</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-19"> Geryon shall have three Hedes agayne,</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-20"> Till Hapsburge makyth them but twayne</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-21"> Seven and Ten makes Seventeen, which I explain Seventeen Hundred, and this Number added to Nine, makes the Year we are now in;_</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-22"> for it must be understood of the Natural Year, which begins the First of <hi rend="underline">January</hi>._<hi rend="underline">Tamys Rivere twys</hi>, &amp;c. The River <hi rend="underline">Thames</hi> frozen twice in one Year, so as Men to walk on it, is a very signal Accident;_</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-23"> which perhaps hath not fallen out for several Hundred Years, before and is the Reason why some Astrologers have thought that this Prophecy could never be fulfilled, because they imagined such a Thing would never happen in our Climate._<hi rend="underline">From Toune of Stoffe</hi>, &amp;c This is a plain Designation of the Duke of <ref target="#spp-102-40L2-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-footnote-1">This we conceive to mean the present Duke, from the late Honours shower'd down on his deserved Merit.</note><hi rend="underline">Marlborough</hi>:_</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-24"> One kind of Stuff used to fatten Land, is called <hi rend="underline">Marle</hi>, and every Body khows that <hi rend="underline">Borough</hi> is a Name for a Town;_</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-25"> and this way of Expression is after the usual dark Manner of old Astrological Predictions._<hi rend="underline">Than shall the Fyshe</hi>, &amp;c. By the <hi rend="underline">Fish</hi> is understood the <hi rend="underline">Dolphin</hi> of <hi rend="underline">Fracne</hi>, as their Kings Eldest Sons are called:_</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-26"> 'Tis here said, he shall lament the Loss of the Duke of <hi rend="underline">Burgundy</hi>, called the <hi rend="underline">Bosse</hi>, which is an old <hi rend="underline">English</hi> Word for <hi rend="underline">Hump-Shoulder</hi>, or <hi rend="underline">Crook-Back</hi>, as that Duke is known to be;_</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-27"> and the Prophecy seems to mean, that he shall be overcome or slain._</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-28"> By the <hi rend="underline">Green Berrys</hi> in the next Line is meant the young Duke of <hi rend="underline">Berry</hi>, the <hi rend="underline">Dauphin</hi>'s Third Son, who shall not have Valour or Fortune enough to supply the Loss of his Eldest Brother._<hi rend="underline">Young Symnele</hi>, &amp;c. By <ref target="#spp-102-40L2-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-footnote-2">This likewise we conceive, from a late Copy of this Prophecy, may allude to the eldest Son of the Chevalier <hi rend="underline">de St. George</hi>, who now makes no small Figure in <hi rend="underline">Italy</hi>.</note><hi rend="underline">Symnel</hi> is meant the Pretended Prince of <hi rend="underline">Wales</hi>, who, if he offers to attempt any Thing against <hi rend="underline">England</hi>, shall miscarry as he did before._<hi rend="underline">Lambert Symnel</hi> is the Name of a young Man noted in our Histories for personating the Son (as I remember) of <hi rend="underline">Edward</hi> the Fourth._<hi rend="underline">And Norway's Pryd</hi>, &amp;c. I cannot guess who is meant by <ref target="#spp-102-40L2-footnote-3">3</ref><note place="foot" n="3" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-footnote-3"><hi rend="underline">Norway's Pride</hi>, tho' at such a Distance of Time, must most evidently point out to us Cardinal <hi rend="underline">Fleury</hi>, the greatest Minister <hi rend="underline">France</hi> ever produced.</note><hi rend="underline">Norway's Pride</hi>, perhaps the Reader may, as well as the Sense of the two following Lines._<hi rend="underline">Reaums shall</hi>, &amp;c. <hi rend="underline">Reaums</hi>, or, as the Word is now, <hi rend="underline">Realms</hi>, is the Old Name for <hi rend="underline">Kingdoms</hi>:_</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-29"> And this is a very plain Prediction of our happy <hi rend="underline">Union</hi>, with the Felicities that shall attend it._</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-30"> It is added, That <hi rend="underline">Old England</hi> shall be no more, and yet no Man shall be sorry for it._</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-31"> And indeed properly speaking, <hi rend="underline">England</hi> is now no more,_</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-32"> for the whole Island is one Kingdom, under the Name of <hi rend="underline">Britain</hi>._<hi rend="underline">Geryon shall</hi>, &amp;c. This Prediction, though somewhat obscure, is wonderfully adapt:_<hi rend="underline">Geryon</hi> is said to have been a King of <hi rend="underline">Spain</hi>, whom <hi rend="underline">Hercules</hi> slew._</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-33"> It was a Fiction of the Poets, that he had Three Heads, which the Author says he shall have again;_</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-34"> that is, <hi rend="underline">Spain</hi> shall have three Kings;_</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-35"> which is now wonderfully verify'd:_</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-36"> For besides the King of <hi rend="underline">Portugal</hi>, which properly is Part of <hi rend="underline">Spain</hi>, there are now two Rivals for <hi rend="underline">Spain</hi>;<ref target="#spp-102-40L2-footnote-4">4</ref><note place="foot" n="4" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-footnote-4"><hi rend="underline">Charles</hi> being dead, <hi rend="underline">Lewis</hi> XV. is the Comperitor; so that our Prophecy still holds good.</note><hi rend="underline">_</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Philip</hi>:_</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-37"> Charles</l><l n="38" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-38"> But <hi rend="underline">Charles</hi> being descended from the Count of <hi rend="underline">Hapsburgh</hi>, Founder of the <hi rend="underline">Austrian</hi> Family, shall soon make those Heads but Two;_</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-39"> by Overcoming <hi rend="underline">Philip</hi>, and Driving him out of <hi rend="underline">Spain</hi>._Some of these Predictions are already fulfilled;_</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-40"> and it is highly probable the rest may be in due Time:_</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-41"> And I think, I have not forced the Words by my Explication into any other Sense than what they will naturally bear._</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-42"> If this be granted, I am sure it must be also allow'd, that the Author was a Person of Extraordinary Sagacity;_</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-43"> and that Astrology brought to such a Perfection as this, is by no means an Art to be despis'd._<gap/></l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-44"> As to the Tradition of these Lines, having been writ in the Original by St. <hi rend="underline">Patrick</hi>,_</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-45"> I confess, I lay not much Weight upon it:_</l><l n="46" xml:id="spp-102-40L2-line-46"> But it is enough to justify their Authority, that the Book from whence I have transcribed them, was printed 170 Years ago, as appears by the Title-Page.<gap/><gap/><gap/>102-40L2   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
