<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <hi rend="underline">The Bank Thrown Down</hi>
        </title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="287-ROGP" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">TO AN EXCELLENT NEW TUNE</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-1"> Pray, what is this Bank of which the town rings?&#13;</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-2"> The banks of a river I know are good things,</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-3"> But a pox o' those banks that choke up the springs.Some mischief is brewing, the project smells rank,To shut out the river by raising the bank.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="4" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-4">The dams and the weirs must all be your own,&#13;</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-5"> You get all the fish, and others get none.</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-6"> We look for a salmon, you leave us a stone.But thanks to the House, the projectors look blank,And thanks to the members that kicked down the Bank.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="7" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-7">This Bank is to make us a new paper mill,&#13;</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-8"> This paper, they say, by the help of a quill,</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-9"> The whole nation's pocket with money will fill.But we doubt that our purses will quickly grow lank,If nothing but paper comes out of this bank.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="10" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-10">'Tis happy to see the whole kingdom in rags,&#13;</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-11"> For rags will make paper, and pa-ba-ba-brags,</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-12"> This paper will soon make us richer than Craggs.From a bo-bo-bo-boy he pursues his old hank,And now he runs mad for a ba-ba-ba-bank.</l></lg><lg n="5" type="stanza"><l n="13" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-13">Oh! then but to see how the beggars will vapour,&#13;</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-14"> For beggars have rags and rags will make paper.</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-15"> And paper makes money, and what can be cheaper?Methinks I now see them so jovial and crank,And riding on horseback to hell and the Bank.</l></lg><lg n="6" type="stanza"><l n="16" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-16">But the cobbler was angry, and swore he had rather&#13;</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-17"> As they did in old times, make money of leather,</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-18"> For then he could coin and could cobble together;And then he could pay for the liquor he drankWith the scrap of a sole, and a fig for a bank.</l></lg><lg n="7" type="stanza"><l n="19" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-19">By a parliament man when the farmer was told,&#13;</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-20"> That paper would quickly be dearer than gold,</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-21"> He wondered for how much an inch would be sold:Then plodding, he thought on a whimsical prankTo turn to small money a bill on the Bank.</l></lg><lg n="8" type="stanza"><l n="22" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-22">For nicely computing the price by retail,&#13;</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-23"> He found he could purchase two tankards of ale,</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-24"> With a scrap of bank paper the breadth of his nail;But the tapster well cudgelled him both side and flank,And made him to curse the poor innocent Bank.</l></lg><lg n="9" type="stanza"><l n="25" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-25">The ghost of old Demar, who left not his betters,&#13;</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-26"> When it heard of a Bank, appeared to his debtors,</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-27"> And lent them for money the backs of his letters:His debtors they wondered to find him so frank,For old Nick gave the papers the mark of the Bank.</l></lg><lg n="10" type="stanza"><l n="28" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-28">In a Chancery bill your attorney engages,&#13;</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-29"> For so many sixpences, so many pages,</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-30"> But sixpence a letter is monstrous high wages:Those that dropped in the South Sea discovered this plank,By which they might swimmingly land on a Bank.</l></lg><lg n="11" type="stanza"><l n="31" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-31">But the squire he was cunning and found what they meant,&#13;</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-32"> That a pack of sly knaves should get fifty per cent,</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-287-ROGP-line-33"> While his tenants in paper must pay him his rent:So for their quack bills he knows whom to thank,For those are but quacks, who mount on a Bank.287-ROGP   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
