<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>V<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ERSES</hi> occasioned by the sudden drying</title>
        <title>up of S<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">T. </hi>P<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ATRICK'S </hi>W<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ELL</hi> near Tri-</title>
        <title>nity College, <hi rend="underline">Dublin</hi>, in 1726.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="KEnoch"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-1 #spp-789-1151-line-1"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-2 #spp-789-1151-line-4"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-3 #spp-789-1151-line-5"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-3 #spp-789-1151-line-6"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-4 #spp-789-1151-line-6"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-5 #spp-789-1151-line-8"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-6 #spp-789-1151-line-20"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-7 #spp-789-1151-line-22"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-8 #spp-789-1151-line-36"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-9 #spp-789-1151-line-64"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-10 #spp-789-1151-line-89"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-11 #spp-789-1151-line-90"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="789-1151" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">B</hi>Y holy Zeal inspir'd, and led by Fame<ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-1"><hi rend="underline">Festus Avienus</hi> flourished in 370. See his Poem de <hi rend="underline">oris Maritimis</hi>, where he uses this Expression concerning <hi rend="underline">Ireland, Insula sacra et sic Insulam dixere Prisci; eamque late Gens Hibernorum colit</hi>.</note>,</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-2"> To thee, once fav'rite Isle, with Joy I came;</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-3"> What Time the <hi rend="underline">Goth</hi>, the <hi rend="underline">Vandal</hi>, and the <hi rend="underline">Hun</hi>,</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-4"> Had my own native <ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-2"><hi rend="underline">Italy</hi> was not properly the native Place of St. <hi rend="underline">Patrick</hi>, but the Place of his Education, and whence he received his Mission; and because he had his new Birth there, hence, by poetical Licence, and by Scripture Figure, our Author calls that Country his native <hi rend="underline">Italy</hi>.</note><hi rend="underline">Italy</hi> o'er-run.<hi rend="underline">Ierne</hi>, to the World's remotest Parts,</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-5" rend="indent(1)"> Renown'd for Valour, <ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-3">3</ref><note place="foot" n="3" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-3" rend="indent(1)"><hi rend="underline">Julius Solinus</hi>, who lived about the Time of <hi rend="underline">Tacitus</hi>, in the Year 80, Chap. 21, speaking of the <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> as a warlike Nation, says, that the Wives in <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>, when delivered of a Son, give the Child its first Food off the Point of their Husband's Swords. <hi rend="underline">Puerpera, si quando Marem edidit, primos Cibos Gladio imponit mariti, inque os Parvuli summo mucrone auspicium alimentorum leviter infert et Gentilibus votis oppetat, non aliter quam in Bello et inter Arma mortem oppetat</hi>. Again, <hi rend="underline">Pr<unclear>ae</unclear>cipua viris Gloria est Armorum tutela·_Polydore Virgil</hi> says, they were distinguished for their Skill in Musick. <hi rend="underline">Hiberni sunt Music<unclear>ae</unclear> peritissimi</hi>. So <hi rend="underline">Giraldus Cambrensis</hi>, who was Preceptor to King <hi rend="underline">John</hi>, in his <hi rend="underline">Topographia Hiberni<unclear>ae</unclear></hi>, Chap. 11. <hi rend="underline">In Musicis solum pr<unclear>ae</unclear> omni Natione, quam vidimus incomparabiliter est instructa Gens h<unclear>ae</unclear>c</hi>.</note> Policy and Arts.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="6" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-6" rend="indent(4)">H<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ITHER</hi> from <ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-3">3</ref><note place="foot" n="3" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-3" rend="indent(2)"><hi rend="underline">Orpheus</hi>, or the antient Author of the <hi rend="underline">Greek</hi> Poem on the <hi rend="underline">Argonautic</hi> Expedition, whoever he be, says, that <hi rend="underline">Jason</hi>, who manned the Ship <hi rend="underline">Argos</hi> at <hi rend="underline">Thessaly</hi>, sailed to <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>. And <hi rend="underline">Adrianus Junius</hi> says the same Thing in these Lines._<hi rend="underline">Illa ego sum Graiis, olim glacialis Ierne_Dicta, et Jasoni<unclear>ae</unclear> Puppis bene cognita Nautis</hi>.</note><hi rend="underline">Colchos</hi>, with the fleecy Ore,<hi rend="underline">Jason</hi> arriv'd two thousand Years before.<ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-4">4</ref><note place="foot" n="4" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-4"><hi rend="underline">Tacitus</hi>, in the Life of <hi rend="underline">Julius Agricola</hi> says, that the Harbours of <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>, on Account of their Commerce, were better known to the trading Part of the World, than those of <hi rend="underline">Britain. Solum, c<unclear>oe</unclear>lumque, &amp; ingenia cultusque Hominum, haud multum a Britannia differunt; melius aditus, portusque per Commercia et Negociatores cogniti</hi>.</note> Thee, happy Island, <hi rend="underline">Pallas</hi> call'd her own,</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-7"> When haughty <hi rend="underline">Britain</hi> was a Land unknown.</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-8" rend="indent(1)"> From thee, with Pride, the <ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-5">5</ref><note place="foot" n="5" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-5"><hi rend="underline">Fordon</hi> in his <hi rend="underline">Scoti-Chronicon, Hector Boethius, Buchanan</hi>, and all the <hi rend="underline">Scotch</hi> Historians agree, that <hi rend="underline">Fergus</hi>, Son of <hi rend="underline">Ferquard</hi> King of <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>, was the first King of <hi rend="underline">Scotland</hi>, which Country he subdued. That he began to reign 330 Years before the Christian <unclear>AE</unclear>ra, and in returning to visit his native Country, was shipwreck'd on those Rocks in the County of <hi rend="underline">Antrim</hi>, which from that Accident have been since named <hi rend="underline">Carrickfergus</hi>. His Descendants reigned after him in <hi rend="underline">Scotland</hi>; for the Crown was settled on him and his lineal Successors. See the List of the Kings of <hi rend="underline">Scotland</hi> in <hi rend="underline">Hector Boethius</hi> and <hi rend="underline">George Buchanan</hi>, which begins thus: 1. <hi rend="underline">Fergusius Primus Scotorum Rex, filius Ferquardi Regis Hiberni<unclear>ae</unclear>, regnare incepit anno ante Christi Servatoris in carnem adventum trecentesimo trigesimo. Regnavit annis </hi>xxv.<hi rend="underline"> et naufragio periit ad Scopulum Fergusis (Cragfergus vernacule) in mari Hiberni<unclear>ae</unclear></hi>._The <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> Language and Habit are still retained in the Northern Parts of <hi rend="underline">Scotland</hi>, where the <hi rend="underline">Highlanders</hi> speak the <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> Tongue, and use their antient Dress. As to the Name <hi rend="underline">Scotland, Camden de Hibernia</hi> mentions it from the Authority of <hi rend="underline">Isidore</hi> and <hi rend="underline">Beda</hi>, that they called <hi rend="underline">Ireland Scotia</hi>, and that <hi rend="underline">Scotland</hi> was termed <hi rend="underline">Scotia a Scotis Incolis, et inde Scoti<unclear>ae</unclear> nomen cum Scotis in Britanniam nostram commigrasse</hi>. Bede, Lib. 1. cap. 1. says, <hi rend="underline">Hibernia propria Scotorum Patria</hi>.</note><hi rend="underline">Caledonians</hi> trace</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-9"> The glorious Founder of their kingly Race:</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-10"> Thy martial Sons, whom now they dare despise,</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-11"> Did once their Land subdue and civilize:</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-12"> Their Dress, their Language, and the <hi rend="underline">Scottish</hi> Name,</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-13"> Confess the Soil from whence the Victors came.</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-14"> Well may they boast that antient Blood which runs</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-15"> Within their Veins, who are thy younger Sons,</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-16"> A Conquest and a Colony from thee,</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-17"> The Mother-Kingdom left her Children free,</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-18"> From thee no Mark of Slavery they felt,</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-19"> Not so with thee thy base Invaders dealt;</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-20"> Invited here to vengeful <hi rend="underline">Morrough</hi>'s Aid<ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-6">6</ref><note place="foot" n="6" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-6">In the Reign of King <hi rend="underline">Henry</hi> II. <hi rend="underline">Dermot M`Murrough</hi>, King of <hi rend="underline">Leinster</hi>, being deprived of his Kingdom by <hi rend="underline">Roderick O Connor</hi>, King of <hi rend="underline">Connaught</hi>, he invited the <hi rend="underline">English</hi> over as Auxiliaries, and promised <hi rend="underline">Richard Strangbow</hi>, Earl of <hi rend="underline">Pembroke</hi>, his Daughter, and all his Dominions as a Portion. By this Assistance <hi rend="underline">M`Murrough</hi> recovered his Crown, and <hi rend="underline">Strangbow</hi> became possessed of all <hi rend="underline">Leinster</hi>. After this, more Forces being sent into <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>, the <hi rend="underline">English</hi> became powerful here; and when <hi rend="underline">Henry</hi> II. arrived, the <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> Princes submitted to his Government, and began to use the <hi rend="underline">English</hi> Laws.</note>,</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-21"> Those whom they could not conquer, they betray'd.<hi rend="underline">Britain</hi>, by thee we fell, ungrateful Isle!</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-22"> Not by thy Valour, but superior Guile;<hi rend="underline">Britain</hi>, with Shame confess this Land of mine<ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-7">7</ref><note place="foot" n="7" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-7">St. <hi rend="underline">Patrick</hi> arrived in <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> in the Year 431, and compleated the Conversion of the Natives, which had been begun by <hi rend="underline">Palladius</hi> and others. And as Bishop <hi rend="underline">Nicholson</hi> observes, (who was better acquainted with the Contents of all the antient Histories of both Kingdoms than any Man of the Age) <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> soon became the Fountain of Learning, to which all the Western Christians, as well as the <hi rend="underline">English</hi>, had Recourse, not only for Instruction in the Principles of Religion, but in all Sorts of Literature; <hi rend="underline">viz. Legendi &amp; Scholastic<unclear>ae</unclear> Eruditionis gratia</hi>. For within a Century after the Death of St. <hi rend="underline">Patrick</hi>, the <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> Seminaries of Learning increased to such a Degree, that most Parts of <hi rend="underline">Europe</hi> sent hither their Children to be educated, and had from hence both their Bishops and Doctors. See venerable <hi rend="underline">Bede</hi>, an <hi rend="underline">English</hi> Historian of undoubted Credit, Hist. Eccles. Lib. 3, cap. 4, 7, 10, 11, 27. Among other <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> Apostles, he says, Saint <hi rend="underline">Columb</hi> converted all the <hi rend="underline">Picts</hi>, and many other <hi rend="underline">Britons</hi>; and that Saint <hi rend="underline">Aidan</hi> was the Instructor of King <hi rend="underline">Oswala</hi>'s <hi rend="underline">Saxon</hi> Subjects in Christianity. <hi rend="underline">Camden de Hibernia</hi> writes, <hi rend="underline">Subsequente <unclear>ae</unclear>tate Scoticis Monarchis nihil Sanctius, nihil Eruditius fuerit, et in universam Europam sanctissimorum virorum Examina emiserint</hi>. He says farther, that they not only repaired to <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>, as to the Mart of Learning, but also brought from thence even the Form of their Letters: <hi rend="underline">Anglosaxones etiam nostri illa <unclear>ae</unclear>tate in Hiberniam tanquam ad bonarum Literarum Mercaturam undique confluxerunt; unde de Viris Sanctis s<unclear>ae</unclear>pissime in nostris Scriptoribus legitur; Amandatus est ad disciplinam in Hiberniam. Indeque nostrates Saxones rationem formandi Literas accepisse videantur, quum eodem plene Charactere usi fuerint, qui hodie Hibernicis est in usu</hi>.</note></l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-23"> First taught thee human Knowledge and divine;</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-24"> My Prelates and my Students, sent from hence,</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-25"> Made your Sons Converts both to God and Sense:</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-26"> Not like the Pastors of thy rav'nous Breed,</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-27"> Who come to fleece the Flocks, and not to feed.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="28" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-28">W<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RETCHED</hi><hi rend="underline">Ierne</hi>! with what Grief I see</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-29"> The fatal Changes Time hath made in thee.</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-30"> The Christian Rites I introduc'd in vain:</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-31"> Lo! Infidelity return'd again.</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-32"> Freedom and Virtue in thy Sons I found,</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-33"> Who now in Vice and Slavery are drown'd.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="34" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-34">B<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">Y</hi> Faith and Prayer, this Crosier in my Hand,</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-35"> I drove the venom'd Serpent from thy Land;</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-36"> The Shepherd in his Bower might sleep or sing<ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-8">8</ref><note place="foot" n="8" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-8">There are no Snakes, Vipers or Toads in <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>; and even Frogs were not known here until about the Year 1700. The Magpyes came a short Time before, and the <hi rend="underline">Norway</hi> Rats since.</note>,</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-37"> Nor dread the Adder's Tooth, or Scorpion's Sting.</l></lg><lg n="5" type="stanza"><l n="38" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-38">W<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">ITH</hi> Omens oft I strove to warn thy Swains,</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-39"> Omens, the Types of thy impending Chains,</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-40"> I sent the Magpye from the <hi rend="underline">British</hi> Soil,</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-41"> With restless Beak thy blooming Fruit to spoil;</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-42"> To din thine Ears with unharmonious Clack,</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-43"> And haunt thy holy Walls in white and black.</l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-44"> What else are those thou seest in Bishop's Geer,</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-45"> Who crop the Nurseries of Learning here?</l><l n="46" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-46"> Aspiring, greedy, full of senseless Prate,</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-47"> Devour the Church, and chatter to the State.</l></lg><lg n="6" type="stanza"><l n="48" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-48">A<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">S</hi> you grew more degenerate and base,</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-49"> I sent you Millions of the croaking Race;</l><l n="50" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-50"> Emblems of Insects vile, who spread their Spawn</l><l n="51" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-51"> Through all thy Land, in Armour, Fur and Lawn;</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-52"> A nauseous Brood that fills your Senate Walls,</l><l n="53" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-53"> And in the Chambers of your Viceroy crawls.</l></lg><lg n="7" type="stanza"><l n="54" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-54">S<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">EE</hi> where that new devouring Vermin runs,</l><l n="55" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-55"> Sent in my Anger from the Land of <hi rend="underline">Huns</hi>;</l><l n="56" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-56"> With harpy Claws they undermine the Ground,</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-57"> And sudden spread a numerous Offspring round;</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-58"> Th' amphibious Tyrant, with his rav'nous Band,</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-59"> Drains all thy Lakes of Fish, of Fruits thy Land.</l></lg><lg n="8" type="stanza"><l n="60" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-60">W<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">HERE</hi> is the sacred Well that bore my Name?</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-61"> Fled to the Fountain back, from whence it came!</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-62"> Fair Freedom's Emblem once, which smoothly flows,</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-63"> And Blessings equally on all bestows.</l><l n="64" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-64"> Here, from the neighbouring <ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-9">9</ref><note place="foot" n="9" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-9">The University of <hi rend="underline">Dublin</hi>, called <hi rend="underline">Trinity College</hi>, was founded by Queen <hi rend="underline">Elizabeth</hi> in 1591.</note> Nursery of Arts,</l><l n="65" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-65"> The Students drinking, rais'd their Wit and Parts;</l><l n="66" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-66"> Here, for an Age and more, improv'd their Vein,</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-67"> Their <hi rend="underline">Ph<unclear>oe</unclear>bus</hi> I, my Spring their <hi rend="underline">Hippocrene</hi>,</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-68"> Discourag'd Youths, now all their Hopes must fail,</l><l n="69" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-69"> Condemn'd to Country Cottages and Ale;</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-70"> To foreign Prelates make a slavish Court,</l><l n="71" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-71"> And by their Sweat procure a mean Support;</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-72"> Or, for the Classicks read th' Attorney's Guide;</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-73"> Collect Excise, or wait upon the Tide.</l></lg><lg n="9" type="stanza"><l n="74" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-74">O! had I been Apostle to the <hi rend="underline">Swiss</hi>,</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-75"> Or hardy <hi rend="underline">Scot</hi>, or any Land but this;</l><l n="76" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-76"> Combin'd in Arms, they had their Foes defy'd,</l><l n="77" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-77"> And kept their Liberty, or bravely dy'd.</l><l n="78" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-78"> Thou still with Tyrants in Succession curst,</l><l n="79" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-79"> The last Invaders trampling on the first:</l><l n="80" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-80"> Nor fondly hope for some Reverse of Fate,</l><l n="81" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-81"> Virtue herself would now return too late.</l><l n="82" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-82"> Not half thy Course of Misery is run,</l><l n="83" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-83"> Thy greatest Evils yet are scarce begun.</l><l n="84" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-84"> Soon shall thy Sons, the Time is just at Hand,</l><l n="85" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-85"> Be all made Captives in their native Land,</l><l n="86" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-86"> When, for the Use of no <hi rend="underline">Hibernian</hi> born,</l><l n="87" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-87"> Shall rise one Blade of Grass one Ear of Corn;</l><l n="88" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-88"> When Shells and Leather shall for Money pass.</l><l n="89" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-89"> Nor thy Oppressing Lords <ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-10">10</ref><note place="foot" n="10" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-10"><hi rend="underline">Wood</hi>'s ruinous Project against the People of <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi>, was supported by Sir <hi rend="underline">Robert Walpole</hi> in 1724.</note> afford thee Brass.</l><l n="90" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-90"> But all turn Leasers to that <ref target="#spp-789-1151-footnote-11">11</ref><note place="foot" n="11" xml:id="spp-789-1151-footnote-11">The Absentees, who spend the Income of their <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> Estates, Places and Pensions in <hi rend="underline">England</hi>.</note> Mongril Breed,</l><l n="91" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-91"> Who from thee sprung, yet on thy Vitals feed;</l><l n="92" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-92"> Who to yon rav'nous Isle thy Treasures bear,</l><l n="93" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-93"> And waste in Luxury thy Harvests there;</l><l n="94" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-94"> For Pride and Ignorance a Proverb grown,</l><l n="95" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-95"> The Jest of Wits, and to the Court unknown.</l></lg><lg n="10" type="stanza"><l n="96" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-96">I <hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">SCORN</hi> thy spurious and degenerate Line,</l><l n="97" xml:id="spp-789-1151-line-97"> And from this Hour my Patronage resign.789-1151   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
