<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>VERSES ON THE SUDDEN DOF</title>
        <title>ST. PATRICK'S-WELL,<lb/></title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="NSweeney"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-1 #spp-789-79L2-line-4"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-2 #spp-789-79L2-line-6"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-3 #spp-789-79L2-line-9"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-4 #spp-789-79L2-line-15"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-5 #spp-789-79L2-line-17"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-6 #spp-789-79L2-line-22"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-7 #spp-789-79L2-line-27"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-8 #spp-789-79L2-line-38"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-9 #spp-789-79L2-line-62"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-10 #spp-789-79L2-line-86"/>
          <link target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-11 #spp-789-79L2-line-87"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="789-79L2" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">B</hi>Y holy zeal inspir'd, and led by fame,</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-2"> To thee, once favourite isle, with joy I came;</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-3"> What time the Goth, the Vandal, and the Hun,</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-4"> Had my own native Italy <ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-1">Italy was not properly the native place of St. Patrick, but the place of his education, and where he received his mission; and because he had his new birth there, hence, by poetical licence, and by scripture-figure, our author calls that country his native Italy. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note> o'er-run.</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-5"> Ierne, to the world's remotest parts,</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-6"> Renown'd for valour, policy, and arts.Hither from Colchos<ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-2">Orpheus, or the antient author of the Greek poem on the Argonautic expedition, whoever he be, says, that Jason, who manned the ship Argos at Thessaly, sailed to Ireland. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note>, with the fleecy ore,</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-7"> Jason arriv'd two thousand years before.</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-8"> Thee, happy island, Pallas call'd her own,</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-9"> When haughty Britain was a land unknown<ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-3">3</ref><note place="foot" n="3" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-3">Tacitus, in the life of Julius Agricola, says, that the harbours of Ireland, on account of their commerce, were better known to the world than those of Britain. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note>:</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-10"> From thee, with pride, the Caledonians trace</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-11"> The glorious founder of their kingly race:</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-12"> Thy martial sons, whom now they dare despise,</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-13"> Did once their land subdue and civilize:</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-14"> Their dress, their language, and the Scottish <hi rend="underline">name</hi>,</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-15"> Confess the soil from whence the victors came<ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-4">4</ref><note place="foot" n="4" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-4">The argument here turns on, what the author of course took for granted, the present Scots being the descendants of Irish emigrants. This fact, however true, was not in Dr. Swift's time ascertained with any degree of precision. Ireland even to this day “remains superstitiously devoted to her antient history,” and “wraps herself in the gloom of her own legendary annals.” Mr. Whitaker has displayed an uncommon fund of knowledge on this very curious subject, both in his “History of Manchester,” and in “The Genuine History of the Britons asserted.” N.</note>.</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-16"> Well may they boast that ancient blood, which runs</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-17"> Within their veins, who are thy younger sons<ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-5">5</ref><note place="foot" n="5" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-5">“The Scots (says Dr Robertson) carry their pretensions to antiquity as high as any of their neighbours. Relying upon uncertain legends, and the traditions of their bards, still more uncertain, they reckon up a series of kings several ages <hi rend="underline">before</hi> the birth of Christ; and give a particular detail of occurrences, which happened in their reigns. In the beginning of the sixteenth century, John Major and Hector Boëthius published their Histories of Scotland: the former a succinct and dry writer, the latter a copious and florid one; and both equally credulous. Not many years after, Buchanan undertook the same work; and if his accuracy and impartiality had been in any degree equal to the elegance of his taste, and to the purity and vigour of his style, his history might be placed on a level with the most admired compositions of the ancients. But, instead of rejecting the improbable tales of Chronicle-writers, he was at the utmost pains to adorn them, and hath cloathed with all the beauties and graces of fiction those legends which formerly had only its wildness and extravagance.”──On the authority of Buchanan and his predecessors the historical part of this poem seems founded, as well as the notes signed I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>. some of which, I believe, were written by the Dean himself. N.</note>,</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-18"> A conquest and a colony from thee.</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-19"> The mother-kingdom left her children free;</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-20"> From thee no mark of slavery they felt:</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-21"> Not so with thee thy base invaders dealt;</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-22"> Invited here to vengeful Morrough's aid<ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-6">6</ref><note place="foot" n="6" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-6">In the reign of king Henry II, Dermot M'Morrough, king of Leinster, being deprived of his kingdom by Roderick O'Connor, king of Connaught, he invited the English over as auxiliaries, and promised Richard Strangbow earl of Pembroke his daughter and all his dominions as a portion. By this assistance, M'Morrough recovered his crown, and Strangbow became possessed of all Leinster. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note>,</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-23"> Those whom they could not conquer, they betray'd.</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-24"> Britain, by thee we fell, ungrateful isle!</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-25"> Not by thy valour, but superior guile:</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-26"> Britain, with shame, confess this land of mine</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-27"> First taught thee human knowledge and divine<ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-7">7</ref><note place="foot" n="7" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-7">St. Patrick arrived in Ireland in the year 431, and compleated the conversion of the natives, which had been begun by Palladius and others. And, as bishop Nicholson observes, Ireland soon became the fountain of learning, to which all the Western Christians, as well as the English, had recourse, not only for instructions in the principles of religion, but in all sorts of literature, <hi rend="underline">viz. Legendi et Scholastic<unclear>ae</unclear> eruditionis gratiá</hi>. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note>;</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-28"> My prelates and my students, sent from hence,</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-29"> Made your sons converts both to God and sense:</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-30"> Not like the pastors of thy ravenous breed,</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-31"> Who come to fleece the flocks, and not to feed.Wretched Ierne! with what grief I see</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-32"> The fatal changes Time hath made in thee!</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-33"> The Christian rites I introduc'd in vain:</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-34"> Lo! infidelity return'd again!</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-35"> Freedom and virtue in thy sons I found,</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-36"> Who now in vice and slavery are drown'd.By faith and prayer, this crosier in my hand,</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-37"> I drove the venom'd serpent from thy land;</l><l n="38" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-38"> The shepherd in his bower might sleep or sing<ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-8">8</ref><note place="foot" n="8" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-8">There are no snakes, vipers, or toads, in Ireland; and even frogs were not known here until about the year 1700. The magpyes came a short time before; and the Norway rats since. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note>,</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-39"> Nor dread the adder's tooth, nor scorpion's sting.With omens oft' I strove to warn thy swains,</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-40"> Omens, the types of thy impending chains.</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-41"> I sent the magpye from the British soil,</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-42"> With restless beak thy blooming fruit to spoil;</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-43"> To din thine ears with unharmonious clack,</l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-44"> And haunt thy holy walls in white and black.</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-45"> What else are those thou seest in bishops' geer,</l><l n="46" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-46"> Who crop the nurseries of learning here;</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-47"> Aspiring, greedy, full of senseless prate,</l><l n="48" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-48"> Devour the church, and chatter to the state?As you grew more degenerate and base,</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-49"> I sent you millions of the croaking race;</l><l n="50" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-50"> Emblems of insects vile, who spread their spawn</l><l n="51" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-51"> Through all thy land, in armour, fur, and lawn;</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-52"> A nauseous brood, that fills your senate walls,</l><l n="53" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-53"> And in the chambers of your viceroy crawls!See, where that new-devouring vermin runs,</l><l n="54" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-54"> Sent in my anger from the land of Huns!</l><l n="55" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-55"> With harpy-claws it undermines the ground,</l><l n="56" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-56"> And sudden spreads a numerous offspring round.</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-57"> Th' amphibious tyrant, with his ravenous band,</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-58"> Drains all thy lakes of fish, of fruits thy land.Where is the holy well that bore my name?</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-59"> Fled to the fountain back, from whence it came!</l><l n="60" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-60"> Fair Freedom's emblem once, which smoothly flows,</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-61"> And blessings equally on all bestows.</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-62"> Here, from the neighbouring <ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-9">9</ref><note place="foot" n="9" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-9">The university of Dublin, called Trinity College, was founded by queen Elizabeth in 1591. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note> nursery of arts,</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-63"> The students, drinking, rais'd their wit and parts;</l><l n="64" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-64"> Here, for an age and more, improv'd their vein,</l><l n="65" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-65"> Their Ph<unclear>oe</unclear>bus I, my spring their Hippocrene.</l><l n="66" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-66"> Discourag'd youths! now all their hopes must fail,</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-67"> Condemn'd to country cottages and ale;</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-68"> To foreign prelates make a slavish court,</l><l n="69" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-69"> And by their sweat procure a mean support;</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-70"> Or, for the classicks, read “Th' Attorney's Guide;”</l><l n="71" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-71"> Collect excise, or wait upon the tide.Oh! had I been apostle to the Swiss,</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-72"> Or hardy Scot, or any land but this;</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-73"> Combin'd in arms, they had their foes defied,</l><l n="74" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-74"> And kept their liberty, or bravely died.</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-75"> Thou still with tyrants in succession curst,</l><l n="76" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-76"> The last invaders trampling on the first:</l><l n="77" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-77"> Nor fondly hope for some reverse of fate,</l><l n="78" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-78"> Virtue herself would now return too late.</l><l n="79" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-79"> Not half thy course of misery is run,</l><l n="80" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-80"> Thy greatest evils yet are scarce begun.</l><l n="81" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-81"> Soon shall thy sons (the time is just at hand)</l><l n="82" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-82"> Be all made captives in their native land;</l><l n="83" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-83"> When, for the use of no Hibernian born,</l><l n="84" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-84"> Shall rise one blade of grass, one ear of corn;</l><l n="85" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-85"> When shells and leather shall for money pass,</l><l n="86" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-86"> Nor thy oppressing lords afford thee brass<ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-10">10</ref><note place="foot" n="10" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-10">Wood's ruinous project in 1724. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note>.</l><l n="87" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-87"> But all turn leasers to that <ref target="#spp-789-79L2-footnote-11">11</ref><note place="foot" n="11" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-footnote-11">The absentees, who spent the income of their Irish estates, places, and pensions, in England. I<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">RISH</hi> E<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">D</hi>.</note> mongrel breed,</l><l n="88" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-88"> Who, from thee sprung, yet on thy vitals feed;</l><l n="89" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-89"> Who to yon ravenous isle thy treasures bear,</l><l n="90" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-90"> And waste in luxury thy harvests there;</l><l n="91" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-91"> For pride and ignorance a proverb grown,</l><l n="92" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-92"> The jest of wits, and to the court unknown.I scorn thy spurious and degenerate line,</l><l n="93" xml:id="spp-789-79L2-line-93"> And from this hour my patronage resign.789-79L2   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
