<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Grand Question Debated:</title>
        <title><hi rend="underline">A Barrack</hi> or a <hi rend="underline">Malthouse</hi>.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="EBurnor"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-866-32GW-footnote-1 #spp-866-32GW-line-29"/>
          <link target="#spp-866-32GW-footnote-2 #spp-866-32GW-line-46"/>
          <link target="#spp-866-32GW-footnote-3 #spp-866-32GW-line-128"/>
          <link target="#spp-866-32GW-footnote-4 #spp-866-32GW-line-128"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="866-32GW" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">By Dean S<hi rend="SMALL-CAPS">WIFT</hi>.</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">T</hi>Hus spoke to my lady the knight full of care,</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-2"> Let me have your advice in a weighty affair:</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-3"> This <hi rend="underline">Hamilton</hi>'s bawn, while it sticks on my hand,</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-4"> I lose by the house, what I get by the land;</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-5"> But how to dispose of it to the best bidder,</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-6"> For a barrack or malthouse, we now must consider:</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-7"> First, let me suppose, I make it a malthouse,</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-8"> Here, I have computed the profit will fall t'us;</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-9"> There's nine hundred pound for labour and grain;</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-10"> I increase it to twelve; so three hundred remain;</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-11"> A handsome addition for wine and good cheer,</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-12"> Three dishes a day, and three hundred a year,</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-13"> With a dozen large vessels my vaults shall be stor'd,</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-14"> No little scrub joint shall come on my board;</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-15"> And you, and the Dean, no more shall combine,</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-16"> To stint me at night to one bottle of wine;</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-17"> Nor shall I, for his humour, permit you shou'd purloin</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-18"> A stone and a half of beef from my sirloin.</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-19"> If I make it a barrack, the crown is my tenant:</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-20"> My dear, I have ponder'd again and again on't,</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-21"> In poundage and drawback, I lose half my rent,</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-22"> And, whatever they give me, I must be content,</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-23"> Or join with the court in every debate;</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-24"> And rather than that, I would lose my estate.Thus ended the knight: thus began the meek wife;</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-25"> It must, and it shall be a barrack, my life:</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-26"> I am grown a mere mopes, no company comes,</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-27"> But a rabble of tenants, and rusty dull rums;</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-28"> With parsons, what lady can keep herself clean?</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-29"> I am all over daub'd, when I sit by the <ref target="#spp-866-32GW-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-footnote-1"><hi rend="underline">Dr </hi>Swift<hi rend="underline">, Dean of St. </hi>Patrick<hi rend="underline">'s.</hi>`</note> dean;<gap/><gap/></l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-30"> But if you will give us a barrack, my dear,</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-31"> The captain, I'm sure, will always come here,</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-32"> I then shall not value his deanship a straw;</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-33"> For the captain, I'll warrant, will keep him in awe:</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-34"> Or shou'd he pretend to be brisk and alert,</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-35"> We'll tell him that chaplains should not be so pert;</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-36"> That men of his coat should be minding their pray'rs,</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-37"> And not among ladies to give themselves airs,Thus argu'd my lady, but argu'd in vain;</l><l n="38" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-38"> The knight his opinion resolv'd to maintain.</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-39"> But <hi rend="underline">Hannah</hi>, who listen'd to all that had past,</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-40"> And could not endure so vulgar a taste,</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-41"> As soon as her Ladyship call'd to be drest,</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-42"> Cry'd, madam, why sure, my master's possest;</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-43"> Sir <hi rend="underline">Arthur</hi> the maltster! how fine it would sound?</l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-44"> I'd rather the bawn were sunk under ground:</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-45"> But, madam, I guess'd, there would never come good.</l><l n="46" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-46"> When I saw him so often with <hi rend="underline">Darby</hi> and <ref target="#spp-866-32GW-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-footnote-2">Sir Arthur Atcheson<hi rend="underline">'s Receiver, and one of his tenants.</hi></note><hi rend="underline">Wood</hi>,</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-47"> And now my dream's out; for I was a dream'd,</l><l n="48" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-48"> That I saw a huge rat? O dear, how I scream'd!</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-49"> And after, methought, I lost my new shoes,</l><l n="50" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-50"> And <hi rend="underline">Molly</hi>, she said, I should hear some ill news;</l><l n="51" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-51"> Dear, madam, had you but the spirit to teaze,</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-52"> You might have a barrack, whenever you please,</l><l n="53" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-53"> And, madam, I always believ'd you so stout,</l><l n="54" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-54"> That for twenty denials, you would not give out.</l><l n="55" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-55"> If I had a husband like him, I protest,</l><l n="56" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-56"> 'Till he gave me my will, I would give him no rest,</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-57"> And rather than come in the same pair of sheets,</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-58"> With such a cross man, I would lie in the streets.</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-59"> But, madam, I beg, you'll contrive and invent,</l><l n="60" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-60"> And worry him out, till he gives his consent,</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-61"> Dear madam, whene'er on a barrack I think,</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-62"> An I were to be hang'd, I can't sleep a wink,</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-63"> For if a new Crotchet comes into my brain,</l><l n="64" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-64"> I can't get it out tho' I'd never so fain.</l><l n="65" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-65"> I fancy already a barrack contriv'd</l><l n="66" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-66"> At <hi rend="underline">Hamilton</hi>'s bawn, and the troop is arriv'd:</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-67"> Of this, to be sure, Sir <hi rend="underline">Arthur</hi>, has warning,</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-68"> And waits on the captain, betimes in the morning.</l><l n="69" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-69"> Now see when they meet, how their honours behave;</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-70"> Noble captain, your servant-- Sir <hi rend="underline">Arthur</hi>, your slave.</l><l n="71" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-71"> You honour me much--- the honour is mine.</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-72"> 'Twas a sad rainy night-- but the morning is fine.</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-73"> Pray how does my lady?-- my wife's at your service----.</l><l n="74" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-74"> I think I have seen her Picture at <hi rend="underline">Jervais</hi>,</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-75"> Good morrow, good captain--- I'll wait on you down.</l><l n="76" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-76"> You shan't stir a foot--- you'll think me a clown.</l><l n="77" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-77"> For all the world, captain, not half an inch farther────</l><l n="78" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-78"> You must be obey'd; your servant, Sir <hi rend="underline">Arthur</hi>;</l><l n="79" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-79"> My humble respects to my Lady, unknown;</l><l n="80" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-80"> I hope you will use my house as your own.</l><l n="81" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-81"> --Go bring me my smock, and leave off your prate,</l><l n="82" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-82"> Thou hast certainly gotten a cup in thy pate.</l><l n="83" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-83"> Pray, madam, be quiet; what was it I said?</l><l n="84" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-84"> You had like to have put it quite out of my head.</l><l n="85" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-85"> Next day, to be sure, the captain will come,</l><l n="86" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-86"> At the head of his troop, with his trumpet and drum;</l><l n="87" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-87"> Now, madam, observe, how he marches in state,</l><l n="88" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-88"> The man with the kettle-drum enters the gate,</l><l n="89" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-89"> Dub, dub, a dub dub; the trumpeters follow,</l><l n="90" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-90"> Tantara, tantara; while all the boys halloo.</l><l n="91" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-91"> See, now comes the captain, all daub'd with gold lace,</l><l n="92" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-92"> O la! the sweet gentleman, look in his face,</l><l n="93" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-93"> And see how he rides like a lord of the land,</l><l n="94" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-94"> With the fine flaming sword he holds in his hand,</l><l n="95" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-95"> And his horse, the dear creature, it prances and rears,</l><l n="96" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-96"> With ribbands in knots, at his tail and his ears.</l><l n="97" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-97"> At last comes the troop at the word of command,</l><l n="98" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-98"> Drawn up in our court, till the captain cries, stand.</l><l n="99" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-99"> Your ladyship lifts up the sash to be seen,</l><l n="100" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-100"> For sure I had dizen'd you out like a Queen;</l><l n="101" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-101"> The captain, to shew he was proud of the favour,</l><l n="102" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-102"> Looks up to the window, and cocks up his beaver.</l><l n="103" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-103"> His beaver is cockt, pray, madam, mind that;</l><l n="104" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-104"> For a captain of horse never takes off his hat;</l><l n="105" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-105"> Because he has never a hand that is idle,</l><l n="106" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-106"> For the right holds the sword, and the left holds the bridle;</l><l n="107" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-107"> Then flourishing twice his sword in the air,</l><l n="108" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-108"> As a compliment due to a lady so fair:</l><l n="109" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-109"> How I tremble to think of the blood it has spilt!</l><l n="110" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-110"> Then he lowers the point; then he kisses the hilt.</l><l n="111" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-111"> Your ladyship smiles, and then you begin:</l><l n="112" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-112"> Pray, captain, be please'd to a-light and walk in.</l><l n="113" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-113"> The captain salutes you, with congee profound;</l><l n="114" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-114"> And your ladyship curtsies half way to the ground.<hi rend="underline">Kit</hi>, run to your master, and bid him come to us;</l><l n="115" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-115"> I'm sure he'll be proud of the honour you do us:</l><l n="116" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-116"> And, captain, you'll do us the favour to stay.</l><l n="117" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-117"> And take a short dinner here with us to-day;</l><l n="118" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-118"> You're heartily welcome; but as for good cheer,</l><l n="119" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-119"> You come in the very worst time of the year.</l><l n="120" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-120"> Had I but expected so worthy a guest────</l><l n="121" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-121"> Lord, madam, your ladyship sure is in jest:</l><l n="122" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-122"> You banter me, madam; the kingdom must grant--</l><l n="123" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-123"> You officers, captain, are so complaisant.</l><l n="124" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-124"> Hist, hussy, I think I hear somebody coming---</l><l n="125" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-125"> No, madam, 'tis only Sir <hi rend="underline">Arthur</hi> a humming---</l><l n="126" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-126"> To shorten my tale, for I hate a long story,</l><l n="127" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-127"> The captain, at Dinner, appears in his glory.</l><l n="128" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-128"> The <ref target="#spp-866-32GW-footnote-3">3</ref><note place="foot" n="3" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-footnote-3">Dr <hi rend="underline">Swift</hi>.</note> dean and the <ref target="#spp-866-32GW-footnote-4">4</ref><note place="foot" n="4" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-footnote-4">Dr. <hi rend="underline">Jenny</hi>.</note> doctor have humbled their pride;</l><l n="129" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-129"> For the captain's intreated to sit by their side.</l><l n="130" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-130"> And because he's their betters, you carve for him first;</l><l n="131" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-131"> The parsons, for envy, are ready to burst.</l><l n="132" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-132"> The servants, amaz'd, are scarce ever able,</l><l n="133" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-133"> To keep off their eyes, as he sits at the table.</l><l n="134" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-134"> And <hi rend="underline">Molly</hi> and I do thrust in our nose,</l><l n="135" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-135"> To peep at the captain, in all his fine cloaths.</l><l n="136" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-136"> Dear, madam, 'be sure, he's a fine spoken man;</l><l n="137" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-137"> Do but hear, on the clergy, how glib his tongue ran.<gap/><gap/></l><l n="138" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-138"> And madam, saith he, if such dinners you give,</l><l n="139" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-139"> You'll never want parsons as long as you live:</l><l n="140" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-140"> I ne'er knew a parson without a good nose;</l><l n="141" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-141"> But the Devil's as welcome, wherever he goes.</l><l n="142" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-142"> G-- d-- me, they bid us reform and repent;</l><l n="143" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-143"> But, zounds, by their looks, they never keep lent.</l><l n="144" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-144"> Mr Curate, for all your grave looks, I'm afraid,</l><l n="145" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-145"> You cast a sheep's eye on her ladyship's maid:</l><l n="146" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-146"> I wish she would lend you her lilly white hand,</l><l n="147" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-147"> In mending your gown, and smoothing your band.</l><l n="148" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-148"> For the Dean was so shabby, and look'd like a ninny;</l><l n="149" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-149"> That the captain suppos'd he was curate to <hi rend="underline">Jenny</hi>.</l><l n="150" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-150"> Whenever you see a cassock and gown,</l><l n="151" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-151"> An hundred to one, but it covers a clown.</l><l n="152" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-152"> Observe how a Parson comes into a room:</l><l n="153" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-153"> G--d-- me, he hobbles as bad as my gro<gap/></l><l n="154" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-154"> A scholard, when just from the college broke loose,</l><l n="155" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-155"> Can hardly tell how to cry bo to a goose,</l><l n="156" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-156"> Your <hi rend="underline">Novids</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">Bludurks</hi>, and <hi rend="underline">Omers</hi>, and stuff;</l><l n="157" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-157"> By g--d, they don't signify this pinch of snuff.</l><l n="158" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-158"> To give a young gentleman right education;</l><l n="159" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-159"> The army's the very best school in the nation.</l><l n="160" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-160"> My school master call'd me a dunce and a fool;</l><l n="161" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-161"> But at cuffs, I was always the cock of the school.</l><l n="162" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-162"> I never could take to my books for the blood o'me;</l><l n="163" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-163"> And the puppy confest, he expected no good o'me;<gap/><gap/><gap/><gap/></l><l n="164" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-164"> Now, madam, you'll think it a strange thing to say,</l><l n="165" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-165"> But the sight of a book, makes me sick to this day.Never since I was born, did I hear so much wit;</l><l n="166" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-166"> And, madam, I laugh'd, till I thought I should split.</l><l n="167" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-167"> So then you look'd scornful, and snuff'd at the dean:</l><l n="168" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-168"> As who should say, now am I skinny and lean?</l><l n="169" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-169"> And he durst not so much as open his lips;</l><l n="170" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-170"> And the dean, he was plaguily down in the hips.Thus merciless <hi rend="underline">Hannah</hi> run on in her talk,</l><l n="171" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-171"> Till she heard the dean call, will you ladyship walk.</l><l n="172" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-172"> Her ladyship answers--- I'm just coming down.</l><l n="173" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-173"> Then turning to <hi rend="underline">Hannah</hi>, and forcing a frown.</l><l n="174" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-174"> Altho' it was plain, in her heart she was glad!</l><l n="175" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-175"> Cry'd, Hussy, why sure, the wench is gone mad:</l><l n="176" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-176"> How could these chimera's get into your brains?</l><l n="177" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-177"> Come hither, and take this old gown for your pains;</l><l n="178" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-178"> But if this secret should reach the dean's ears,</l><l n="179" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-179"> He ne'er will have done with his jibes and his jeers.</l><l n="180" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-180"> For your life, not a word of this matter, I charge you:</l><l n="181" xml:id="spp-866-32GW-line-181"> Give me but a Barrack, a fig for the clergy.866-32GW   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
