<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The grand Question debated,</title>
        <title>Whe\<hi rend="underline">del</hi>.·a\ther Hamilton's Bawn shall be turned into a Malt-house<lb/></title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="JW"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="866-800Z" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1">N<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 08. 3.\<hi rend="underline">Swift's hand</hi>\</l></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-1"> Thus spoke to my Lady, the Knight full of care,&#13;</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-2"> Let me have your advice in a weighty affair:</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-3"> This Hamilton's Bawn, while it sticks on my hand,</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-4"> I lose by the house what I get by the land.</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-5"> But, how to dispose of it to the best bidder</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-6"> For a Barrack or Malt-house, we now must consider.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="7" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-7">First, let me suppose I make it a Malt-house,&#13;</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-8"> Here, I have computed the profit will fall t'us:</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-9"> There's nine hundred pounds for labour and Grain,</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-10"> I encrease it to twelve, so three hundred remain:</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-11"> A handsom addition for wine and good chear,</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-12"> Three dishes a day, and three hogsheads a year;</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-13"> With a dosen large vessels my Vault shall be stor'd,</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-14"> No little Scrub Ioynt shall cover my board:</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-15"> And you and the Dean no more shall combine</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-16"> To stint me at night to one bottle of wine</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-17"> Nor shall I for his humor permit you to purloin</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-18"> A Stone and a half of good beef from my Surloyn.If I make it a Barrack, the Crown is my Tenant;</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-19"> My Dear, I have ponder'd again and agen on't:</l><l n="20" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-20"> In poundage and draw-backs I lose half my rent,</l><l n="21" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-21"> Whatever they give me I must be content,</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-22"> Or joyn with the Whigs in ev'ry debate,</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-23"> And rather than that I would lose my estate.Thus ended the Knight: Thus began his meek Wife;</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-24"> It must, and it shall be a Barrack: my Life.</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-25"> I'm grown a meer Mopus; no company comes</l><l n="26" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-26"> But a rabble of tenants, and rusty dull Rumms.</l><l n="27" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-27"> With Parsons what Lady can keep her self clean?</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-28"> I'm all over dawb'd when I sit by the Dean:</l><l n="29" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-29"> And truly, tis plain from his rude conversation</l><l n="30" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-30"> He ne'r was acquainted with women of fashion.</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-31"> But, if you will give us a Barrack, my Dear,</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-32"> The Captain I'm sure will always come here;</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-33"> I then shall not value his Dean-ship a straw,</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-34"> For, the Captain I warrant will keep him in aw;</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-35"> Or should he pretend to be brisk and alert,</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-36"> Will tell him that Chaplains must not be so pert;</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-37"> That, men of his coat should be minding theirs pray'rs,</l><l n="38" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-38"> And not among Ladyes to give themselves Airs.Thus argued my Lady, but argu'd in vain;</l><l n="39" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-39"> The Knight his opinion resolv'd to maintain.But, Hannah who listned to all that had pass't,</l><l n="40" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-40"> And cou'd not endure so vulgar a tast,</l><l n="41" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-41"> As soon as her Ladyship call'd to be dresst,</l><l n="42" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-42"> Cry'd, Madam, why sure my Master's possesst.</l><l n="43" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-43"> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arthur the Malster! how fine it will sound?</l><l n="44" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-44"> I'de rather the Bawn were sunk under ground:</l><l n="45" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-45"> But, Madam, I guesst there would never come good</l><l n="46" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-46"> When I saw him so often with Darby and Wood.</l><l n="47" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-47"> And, now my Dream's out; for I was a-dreamd</l><l n="48" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-48"> That I saw a huge Rat: O dear, how I screamd!</l><l n="49" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-49"> And after, methought I lost my new shoes,</l><l n="50" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-50"> And Molly she said, I should hear some ill news.Dear Madam, had you but the spirit to teize,</l><l n="51" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-51"> You might have a Barrack whenever you please.</l><l n="52" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-52"> And Madam, I always believ'd <del>so st</del>·you so stout,</l><l n="53" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-53"> That for twenty denyals you would not give out.</l><l n="54" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-54"> If I had a husband like him, I purtest</l><l n="55" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-55"> Till he gave me my will, I would give him no rest:</l><l n="56" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-56"> And, rather than come in the same pair of sheets</l><l n="57" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-57"> With such a cross man, I would lye in the streets.</l><l n="58" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-58"> But Madam I beg you, contrive and invent,</l><l n="59" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-59"> And worry him out till he gives his consentDear Madam, when e'r of a Barrack I think,</l><l n="60" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-60"> An I were to be hang'd, I can't sleep a wink:</l><l n="61" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-61"> For if a new crotchet comes into my brain,</l><l n="62" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-62"> I can't get it out, though I'd never so fain.</l><l n="63" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-63"> I fancy already a Barrack contriv'd</l><l n="64" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-64"> At Hamiltons Bawn; and the troop is arriv'd.</l><l n="65" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-65"> Of this, to be sure S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arthur has warning</l><l n="66" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-66"> And waits on the Captain betimes the next morning.Now, see when they meet, how their Honors behave.</l><l n="67" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-67"> Noble Captain your servant──S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arthur, your slave──</l><l n="68" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-68"> You honor me much──the honor is mine──</l><l n="69" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-69"> 'T'was a sad rainy night──But the morning is fine──</l><l n="70" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-70"> Pray, how does My Lady? My wife's at your service,──</l><l n="71" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-71"> I think I have seen her Picture by Iervis──</l><l n="72" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-72"> Good morrow good Captain──I'll wait on you down──</l><l n="73" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-73"> You sha'n't stir a foot──You'll think me a clown────</l><l n="74" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-74"> For all the world Captain, not half an Inch farther────</l><l n="75" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-75"> You must be obey'd: your servant S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Arthur;</l><l n="76" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-76"> My humble respects to My Lady unknown──</l><l n="77" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-77"> I hope you will use my house as your own.<unclear>ins with crossGo bring me my smock, and leave off your prate,</unclear></l><l n="78" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-78"> Thou hast certainly gotten a cup in thy pate.</l><l n="79" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-79"> “Pray Madam, be quiet; what was it I said?──</l><l n="80" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-80" rend="indent(1)"> You had like to have put it quite out of my head.<unclear>Next day to be sure the Captain will come</unclear></l><l n="81" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-81"> At the head of his Troop with trumpet and drum,</l><l n="82" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-82"> Now Madam, observe how he marches in state</l><l n="83" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-83"> The Man with the Kettle-drum enters the gate;</l><l n="84" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-84"> Dub Dub a Dub Dub: the trumpeters follow</l><l n="85" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-85"> Tantara Tantara, while all the boys hollah:</l><l n="86" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-86"> See, now comes the Captain all dawb'd with gold lace;</l><l n="87" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-87"> O Law, the sweet Gentleman! look in his face:</l><l n="88" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-88"> And see how he rides like a Lord of the Land</l><l n="89" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-89"> With the fine flaming sword that he holds in his hand</l><l n="90" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-90"> And his horse, the dear Cretor, it prances and rears</l><l n="91" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-91"> With ribbins in knots at it's tail and its ears,</l><l n="92" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-92"> At last comes the troop, by the word of command</l><l n="93" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-93"> Drawn up in our court, till the Captain cryes, stand.</l><l n="94" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-94"> Your Ladyship lifts up the sash, to be seen;</l><l n="95" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-95"> For, sure I had dizen'd you out like a Queen</l><l n="96" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-96"> The Captain to show he is proud of the favour</l><l n="97" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-97"> Looks up to your window, and cocks up his Be<add>a</add>ver:</l><l n="98" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-98"> (His Beaver is cock't; pray Madam mark that;</l><l n="99" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-99"> For a Captain of horse never takes off his hat,</l><l n="100" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-100"> Because he has never a hand that is idle,</l><l n="101" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-101"> For, the right holds his sword, and the left holds his Bridle)</l><l n="102" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-102"> Then flourishes thrice his sword in the air</l><l n="103" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-103"> As a compliment due to a Lady so fair</l><l n="104" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-104"> How I tremble to think of the blood it hath spilt!</l><l n="105" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-105"> Then he low'rs down the point, and kisses the hilt.</l><l n="106" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-106"> Your Ladyship smiles, and thus you begin;</l><l n="107" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-107"> Pray Captain be pleas'd to light and walk in.</l><l n="108" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-108"> The Captain salutes you with Congee profound</l><l n="109" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-109"> And your Ladyship Curchyes half way to the ground.Kitt; run for your Master and bid him come to us.</l><l n="110" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-110"> I'm sure he'll be proud of this honour you do us</l><l n="111" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-111"> And, Captain, you'll do us the favour to stay</l><l n="112" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-112"> And take a short dinner here with us to day:</l><l n="113" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-113"> You're heartily welcom: but as for good chear,</l><l n="114" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-114"> You're come in the very worst time of the year.</l><l n="115" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-115"> If I had but expected so worthy a Guest──</l><l n="116" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-116"> Lord──Madam──your Ladyship sure is in jest.</l><l n="117" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-117"> You banter me Madam──the Kingdom must grant──</l><l n="118" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-118"> You officers, Captain, are so complaisant──<unclear>ins with fancyasteriskHist, Huzzy, I think I hear some-body coming────</unclear></l><l n="119" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-119" rend="indent(1)"> No, Madam; 'tis only Sir Arthur a humming.<unclear>To shorten my tale, (for I hate a long story)</unclear></l><l n="120" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-120"> The Captain at dinner appears in his glory.</l><l n="121" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-121"> The Dean and the Doctor have humbled their pride</l><l n="122" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-122"> For the Captain's entreated to sit by your side.</l><l n="123" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-123"> And because he's their betters, you carve for him first:</l><l n="124" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-124"> The Parsons for envy are ready to burst.</l><l n="125" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-125"> The servants amaz'd are scarce ever able</l><l n="126" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-126"> To keep off their eyes as they wait at the table</l><l n="127" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-127"> And Molly and I have thrust in our nose</l><l n="128" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-128"> To peep at the Captain in all his fine cloze.</l><l n="129" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-129"> Dear Madam, be sure he's a fine-spoken man</l><l n="130" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-130"> Do but hear on the Clergymen how his tongue ran;</l><l n="131" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-131"> Poor creatures they both were as dull as a log,</l><l n="132" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-132"> And had not a word to throw at a dog.</l><l n="133" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-133"> And Madam says he, if such dinners you give</l><l n="134" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-134"> You'll never want Parsons as long as you live</l><l n="135" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-135"> I ne'r knew a Parson without a good nose,</l><l n="136" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-136"> But the Devil's as welcom where ever he goes</l><l n="137" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-137"> G──d d──mn me they bid us reform and repent,</l><l n="138" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-138"> But Z──ds by their looks, they never keep lent.</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="139" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-139">Mister Curate, for all your grave looks, I'm afraid&#13;</l><l n="140" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-140"> You cast a sheep's eye on her Ladyship's maid,</l><l n="141" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-141"> I wish she would lend you her pretty white hand</l><l n="142" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-142"> In mending your Gown, and smoothing your band</l><l n="143" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-143"> (For, the Dean was so shabby, and lookt like a Ninny</l><l n="144" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-144"> That the Captain suppos'd he was Curate to Ienney)<unclear>ins with simple asterisk</unclear>·Whenever you see a Cassock and gown,</l><l n="145" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-145"> A hundred to one; <unclear/><hi rend="underline">caret·add·by·Swift</hi>·but<unclear/> it covers a Clown;</l><l n="146" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-146"> Observe how a Parson comes into a room,</l><l n="147" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-147"> G──d────me, he hobbles as bad as my Groom;</l><l n="148" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-148"> A Scholard when just from his College broke loose,</l><l n="149" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-149"> Can hardly tell how to cry Bo to a goose;</l><l n="150" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-150"> Your Noveds, and Blutraks, and Omurs and stuff,</l><l n="151" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-151"> By G──they don't signify this pinch of Snuff.</l><l n="152" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-152"> To give a young gentleman right education,</l><l n="153" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-153"> The Army's the only good school in the Nation;</l><l n="154" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-154"> My School Master call'd me a dunce and a fool,</l><l n="155" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-155"> But, at cuffs I was always the cock of the School;</l><l n="156" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-156"> I never cou'd take to my book for the blood o'me,</l><l n="157" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-157"> And the puppy confess'd, he expected no good o'me.<gap/><gap/><gap/><gap/></l><l n="158" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-158"> Now Madam, you'll think it a strange thing to say,</l><l n="159" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-159" rend="indent(1)"> But, the sight of a book makes me sick to this day.<unclear>Never since I was born did I hear so much wit</unclear></l><l n="160" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-160"> And, Madam, I laught till I thought I should split.</l><l n="161" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-161"> So, then you look't scornfull, and snifft at the Dean,</l><l n="162" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-162"> As who should say; now am I skinny and lean?</l><l n="163" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-163"> But he durst not so much as once open his lips,</l><l n="164" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-164"> And the Doctor <unclear>char. del</unclear>·was plaguily deep in the hipps.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="165" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-165">Thus mercyless Hannah ran on in her talk&#13;</l><l n="166" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-166"> Till she heard the Dean call; will your Ladyship walk?</l><l n="167" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-167"> Her Ladyship answers; I'm just coming down;</l><l n="168" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-168"> Then turning to Hannah, and forcing a frown,</l><l n="169" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-169"> Although it was plain in her heart she was glad,</l><l n="170" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-170"> Cry'd, huzzy; why sure the wench is gone mad:</l><l n="171" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-171"> How could these Chimera's get into your Brains──</l><l n="172" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-172"> Come hither, and take this old gown for your pains.</l><l n="173" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-173"> But the Dean, if this secret should come to his ears</l><l n="174" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-174"> Will never have done with his Gibes and his Iears.</l><l n="175" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-175"> For your life, not a word of the matter, I charge ye:</l><l n="176" xml:id="spp-866-800Z-line-176"> Give me but a Barrack, a fig for the Clerggy.866-800Z   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
