<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>AY and NO, <hi rend="underline">a Tale from</hi> Dublin; written in 1737.</title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <name key="NSweeney"/>
          <resp>transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes">
          <link target="#spp-843A71H1-footnote-1 #spp-843A71H1-line-3"/>
          <link target="#spp-843A71H1-footnote-2 #spp-843A71H1-line-4"/>
        </linkGrp>
        <div n="843A71H1" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-1"><hi rend="display-initial">A</hi>T <hi rend="underline">Dublin's</hi> high feast sat Primate and Dean,</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-2"> Both dress'd like divines, with band and face clean.</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-3"> Quoth <hi rend="underline">Hugh</hi> of <hi rend="underline">Armagh</hi><ref target="#spp-843A71H1-footnote-1">1</ref><note place="foot" n="1" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-footnote-1">Dr. <hi rend="underline">Hugh Boulter</hi>, who was a commoner of <hi rend="underline">Christ Church, Oxford</hi>, was chosen a demy of <hi rend="underline">Magdalen College</hi> at the same election with Mr. <hi rend="underline">Addison</hi> and Dr. <hi rend="underline">Wilcox</hi>. He was invited to <hi rend="underline">London</hi> by secretary <hi rend="underline">Hedges</hi> in 1700, to whom he was chaplain; and obtained from the earl of <hi rend="underline">Sunderland</hi> the parsonage of <hi rend="underline">St. Olave, Southwark</hi>, and the arch-_deaconry of <hi rend="underline">Surrey</hi>. He attended king <hi rend="underline">George</hi> I. to <hi rend="underline">Hanover</hi> in 1719, taught the <hi rend="underline">English</hi> language to prince <hi rend="underline">Frederick</hi>; and was promoted to the deanry of <hi rend="underline">Christ Church</hi> and bishoprick of <hi rend="underline">Bristol Oct</hi>. 20, the same year; and to the archbishoprick of <hi rend="underline">Armagh, Aug</hi>. 21, 1724. The latter promotion he would have declined; but his judgement, moderation, and address, being thought necessary to quench the flame which <hi rend="underline">Wood's</hi> ruinous project had occasioned, the king laid his commands on him, to which he reluctantly submitted. He made a visit to his native country in <hi rend="underline">June</hi> 1742, and died in <hi rend="underline">London</hi> the <hi rend="underline">September</hi> following. His public charities in <hi rend="underline">Ireland</hi> amounted to upwards of thirty thousand pounds.──When a young man, he joined with <hi rend="underline">Ambrose Philips</hi>, who was afterwards his secretary, and others, in a Paper called “The Free-thinker,” since collected in three volumes. His “State Letters” have been lately published, in two volumes octavo.</note>, “The mob is grown bold,”</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-4"> “Ay, ay,” quoth the Dean, “the cause is old gold <ref target="#spp-843A71H1-footnote-2">2</ref><note place="foot" n="2" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-footnote-2">To remedy the scarcity of silver coin, the primate supported a scheme at the council-table, to bring gold and silver nearer to a par, by lowering that of the former; which was carried into execution. The populace, encouraged by some dealers in exchange, who were the principal losers, grew clamorous; but, experience evincing the utility of the project, the people soon recovered their senses, and he rose to the greatest height of popularity.</note>.”</l><l n="5" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-5"> “No, no,” quoth the Primate, “if causes we sift,</l><l n="6" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-6"> “This mischief arises from witty Dean <hi rend="underline">Swift</hi>.”</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-7"> The smart one replied, “There's no wit in the case;</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-8"> “And nothing of that ever troubled your Grace.</l><l n="9" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-9"> “Though with your state-sieve your own notions you split,</l><l n="10" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-10"> “A <hi rend="underline">Boulter</hi> by name is no <hi rend="underline">bolter</hi> of wit.</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-11"> “It is matter of weight, and a mere money-job;</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-12"> “But the lower the coin, the higher the mob.</l><l n="13" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-13"> “Go tell your friend <hi rend="underline">Bob</hi> and the other great folk,</l><l n="14" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-14"> “That sinking the coin is a dangerous joke.</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-15"> “The <hi rend="underline">Irish</hi> dear joys have enough common sense,</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-16"> “To treat gold reduced like <hi rend="underline">Wood's</hi> copper pence.</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-17"> “It is pity a Prelate should die without law;</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-843A71H1-line-18"> “But if I say the word──take care of <hi rend="underline">Armagh</hi>!”843A71H1   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
