<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <hi rend="underline">Ode to the King</hi>
          <lb/>
        </title>
        <sponsor>Lafayette College</sponsor>
        <principal>James Woolley</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <resp>proof corrected</resp>
          <name key="TNiese 25JA11"/>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Distributed by Digital Scholarship Services at Lafayette College</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc>
          <additional/>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </correction>
        <normalization>
          <p>To be drafted.</p>
        </normalization>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="book">
        <linkGrp type="notes"/>
        <div n="006-ROGP" type="poem"><head type="note" n="1" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-1"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-1-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="2" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-2"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-2-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head><head type="note" n="3" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-3"><lg n="1" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1" type="headnote"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-headnote-3-line-group-1-line-1"/></lg></head>
      <lg n="1" type="stanza"><l n="1" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-1"> Sure there's some wondrous joy in doing good;&#13;</l><l n="2" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-2"> Immortal joy, that suffers no allay from fears,Nor dreads the tyranny of years,</l><l n="3" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-3"> By none but its possessors to be understood:Else where's the gain in being great?Kings would indeed be victims of the state;What can the poet's humble praise?What can the poet's humble bays?(We poets oft our bays allow,Translated to the hero's brow)Add to the victor's happiness?What do the sceptre, crown and ball,</l><l n="4" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-4"> Rattles for infant royalty to play withal,But serve t' adorn the baby dressOf one poor coronation day,To make the pageant gay:A three hours' scene of empty pride,And then the toys are thrown aside.</l></lg><lg n="2" type="stanza"><l n="5" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-5">II</l></lg><lg n="3" type="stanza"><l n="6" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-6">But the delight of doing good&#13;Is fixed like fate among the stars,And deified in verse;'Tis the best gem in royalty,The great distinguisher of blood,Parent of valour and of fame,Which makes a godhead of a name,</l><l n="7" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-7"> And is contemporary to eternity.This made the ancient Romans to affordTo <hi rend="underline">valour</hi> and to <hi rend="underline">virtue</hi> the same word:</l><l n="8" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-8"> To show the paths of both must be together trod,Before the hero can commence a god.</l></lg><lg n="4" type="stanza"><l n="9" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-9">III</l></lg><lg n="5" type="stanza"><l n="10" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-10">These are the ways&#13;</l><l n="11" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-11"> By which our happy prince carves out his bays;Thus he has fixed his nameFirst, in the mighty list of Fame,</l><l n="12" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-12"> And thus he did the airy goddess court,He sought her out in fight,And like a bold romantic knightRescued her from the giant's fort:The tyrant Death lay crouching down,Waiting for orders at his feet,Spoiled of his leaden crown;He trampled on this haughty Bajazet,Made him his footstool in the war,And a grim slave to wait on his triumphal car.</l></lg><lg n="6" type="stanza"><l n="13" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-13">IV</l></lg><lg n="7" type="stanza"><l n="14" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-14">And now I in the spirit see&#13;(The spirit of exalted poetry)I see the fatal fight begin;</l><l n="15" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-15"> And, lo! where a destroying angel stands,(By all but heaven and me unseen,)</l><l n="16" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-16"> With lightning in his eyes, and thunder in his hands;'In vain', said he, 'does utmost Thule boastNo poisonous beast will in her breed,Or no infectious weed,When she sends forth such a malignant birth,When man himself's the vermin of her earth;When Treason there in person seems to stand,</l><l n="17" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-17"> And Rebel is the growth and manufacture of the land.'He spake, and a dark cloud flung o'er his light,And hid him from poetic sight,And (I believe) began himself the fight,For straight I saw the field maintained,And what I used to laugh at in romance,And thought too great even for the effects of chance,</l><l n="18" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-18"> The battle almost by great William's single valour gained;The angel (doubtless) kept the eternal gate,And stood twixt him and every fate;</l><l n="19" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-19"> And all those flying deaths that aimed him from the field,(The impartial deaths which comeLike love, wrapped up in fire;And like that too, make every breast their home)Broke on his everlasting shield.</l></lg><lg n="8" type="stanza"><l n="20" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-20">V</l></lg><lg n="9" type="stanza"><l n="21" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-21">The giddy British populace,&#13;That tyrant guard on Peace,Who watch her like a prey,And keep her for a sacrifice,And must be sung, like Argus, into ease</l><l n="22" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-22"> Before this milk-white heifer can be stole away,Our prince has charmed its many hundred eyes;Has lulled the monster in a deepAnd (I hope) an eternal sleep,And has at last redeemed the mighty prize.The Scots themselves, that discontented brood,Who always loudest for religion brawl,(As those do still wh'have none at all)Who claim so many titles to be Jews,(But, surely such whom God did never for his people choose)Still murmuring in their wilderness for food,Who pine us like a chronical disease;And one would think 'twere past omnipotence to please;Your presence all their native stubbornness controls,And for a while unbends their contradicting souls:As in old fabulous hell,</l><l n="23" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-23"> When some patrician god would visit the immortal gaol,The very brightness of his faceSuspended every horror of the place,The giants under Etna ceased to groan,And Sisyphus lay sleeping on his stone.</l><l n="24" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-24"> Thus has our prince completed every victory,And glad Iërne now may see</l><l n="25" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-25"> Her sister isles are conquered too as well as she.</l></lg><lg n="10" type="stanza"><l n="26" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-26">VI</l></lg><lg n="11" type="stanza"><l n="27" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-27">How vainly (sir) did your fond enemy try&#13;Upon a rubbish heap of broken lawsTo climb at victoryWithout the footing of a cause;His laurel now must only be a cypress wreath,And his best victory a noble death;His scrap of life is but a heap of miseries,The remnant of a falling snuff,Which hardly wants another puff,And needs must <hi rend="underline">stink</hi> whene'er it dies;Whilst at your victorious lightAll lesser ones expire,Consume, and perish from our sight,Just as the sun puts out a fire;And every foolish fly that dares to aimTo buzz about the mighty flame;</l><l n="28" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-28"> The wretched insects singe their wings, and fall,And humbly at the bottom crawl.</l></lg><lg n="12" type="stanza"><l n="29" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-29">VII</l></lg><lg n="13" type="stanza"><l n="30" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-30">That restless tyrant, who of late&#13;Is grown so impudently great,That tennis-ball of fate;This gilded meteor which fliesAs if it meant to touch the skies;For all its boasted height,For all its plagiary light,Took its first growth and birthFrom the worst excrements of earth;</l><l n="31" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-31"> Stay but a little while and down again 'twill come,</l><l n="32" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-32"> And end as it began, in vapour, stink, and scum.Or has he like some fearful star appeared?</l><l n="33" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-33"> Long dreaded for his bloody tail and fiery beard,Transcending nature's ordinary laws,Sent by just heaven to threaten earthWith war, and pestilence, and dearth,</l><l n="34" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-34"> Of which it is at once the prophet and the cause.Howe'er it be, the pride of FranceHas finished its short race of chance,And all her boasted influences areWrapped in the vortex of the British star;</l><l n="35" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-35"> Her tyrant too an unexpected wound shall feelIn the last wretched remnant of his days;</l><l n="36" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-36"> Our prince has hit him, like Achilles, in the heel,The poisonous darts has made him reel,Giddy he grows, and down is hurled,</l><l n="37" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-37"> And as a mortal to his vile disease,</l><l n="38" xml:id="spp-006-ROGP-line-38"> Falls sick in the posteriors of the world.006-ROGP   </l></lg></div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
